<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Search the Scriptures a treatise shewing that all Christians ought to read the Holy Books : with directions to them therein : in three parts.</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12623055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12623055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 726:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Search the Scriptures a treatise shewing that all Christians ought to read the Holy Books : with directions to them therein : in three parts.</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 193, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64584:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64584:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Search the Scriptures.</hi> A TREATISE Shewing that all CHRISTIANS Ought to READ the HOLY BOOKS; WITH DIRECTIONS To them therein.</p>
            <p>In Three PARTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to His moſt Sacred Majeſty. 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:64584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64584:2"/>
            <head>Introduction.</head>
            <p>THE Holy Scriptures, as the <hi>firſt Homily</hi> of our Church teaches all its Children, in the very beginning of it, are ſuch a Fountain and Well of Truth, that as many as be deſirous to enter into the right and perfect way unto God, muſt apply their minds to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them: without which they can neither ſufficiently know God and his Will, nor their own Office and Duty. <hi>For in Holy Scripture is fully contained, what we ought to do, and what to eſchew; what to believe, what to love, and what to look for at God's hands, at length. And therefore theſe Books ought to be much in our hands, in our eyes, in our ears, in our mouths, but moſt of all in our hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64584:3"/>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which ſort of Diſcourſe, which is grounded upon the VI. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Religion, they of the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> are wont to make a double Exception.</p>
            <p>One is, That there are ſome things neceſſary to be believed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which are not to be found there: but muſt be received from ancient <hi>Traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is, That thoſe Truths which are delivered in the Holy Scriptures, are not ſo clear and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, that common people ſhould be intruſted with the reading of them.</p>
            <p>Now to the <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe, there hath been ſome time ago a plain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer made in a <hi>Diſcourſe about Traditions:</hi> Therefore this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe is intended only as an Anſwer to the
<hi>Second</hi> Exception. For the maintaining of which they are wont to alledge, among other places, thoſe remarkable words of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:64584:3"/>his <hi>Second</hi> Epiſtle, the <hi>Third</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, and
<hi>Sixteenth</hi> Verſe. Where, having made mention of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, which treated of the ſame matter, that he had juſt before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, he ſays, <hi>In which are ſome things hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures, unto their own deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold, ſay they, how dangerous it is for common people to meddle with the Holy Scriptures: which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf to a two edged Sword, ought not to be put into their hands, for fear they deſtroy themſelves therewith.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed the ſame St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches us,
<hi>Rom. XV. 4.</hi> that <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things were written afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, were written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> and <hi>are profitable,</hi> as he writes elſewhere, <hi>2 Tim. III. 16. for doctrine, for reproof, for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb facs="tcp:64584:4"/>for inſtruction in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this notwithſtanding, there are, ſay they, ſuch
<hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>obſcurities</hi> in the Holy Scriptures, as we learn from this great Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that they ought not to be thought profitable for all people; but rather hurtful to them that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: who therefore ought not to read them.</p>
            <p>By which ſingle Inſtance, the Reader may learn, if he mark it well, what ſort of Interpretations of Scripture we are like to have; if we truſt to them alone, and do not ſee with our own eyes: when theſe very words of St. <hi>Peter</hi> do plainly teach us the quite contrary Doctrine to that which they would eſtabliſh by them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> For they are ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Reaſon why the people ſhould not read them, that, <hi>Firſt,</hi> they evidently ſuppoſe the common<pb facs="tcp:64584:4"/>people, even the <hi>unlearned</hi> among them, did in thoſe days read the Scriptures. Elſe they could not have
<hi>wreſted</hi> them: as the Apoſtle ſays they did; and complains of that, but not of their reading them. And</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II. Secondly,</hi> Theſe words do not affirm the whole Scripture to be hard to be underſtood, but only ſome part of it: St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles</hi> at the moſt, or rather the things of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had been treating. And not all of them neither, but only <hi>ſome</hi> things; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome few things which would require pains, and diligent attention of mind, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the meaning of them. And</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III. Thirdly,</hi> The Apoſtle doth not ſay, that all who read thoſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult paſſages, are in danger to wreſt them; but only the unlearned and unſtable; who abuſe the plaineſt Truths to their own ruine. As for<pb facs="tcp:64584:5"/>others, they may read even the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles</hi> ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough; nay, receive great profit from thence, as well as from other Scriptures: and they who wreſt them, are not to leave reading them; but to grow in true Chriſtian knowledge, and in Stability of mind.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>three Parts</hi> of the inſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>In treating and reading of which, <hi>Let us pray to God,</hi> (as the <hi>ſecond Homily</hi> concludes) <hi>that we may ſpeak, think, believe, live, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part hence, according to the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Doctrine and Verities of theſe holy Books. And by that means, in this World, have God's defence, favour and grace, with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable ſolace of peace, and quietneſs of Conſcience; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this miſerable life, enjoy the endleſs Bliſs and Glory of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64584:5"/>
            <head>PART I.</head>
            <p>THat the Right of God's People to read the Holy Scriptures, is not at all prejudiced by theſe words of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> appears from hence: That the <hi>Wreſting of the Scriptures by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unſtable,</hi> doth ſuppoſe, that even ſuch perſons did then read them: Which overthrows the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, which they of the Roman Church, endeavour to draw from this place.</p>
            <p>For there had been no poſſibility of perverting their ſenſe, if they had not been in their hands at that time; as they are in ours now. And yet the Apoſtle doth not reprehend their medling with them; but their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and their heedleſnes: which was the cauſe they miſunderſtood them; and might have been prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a little diligence and care, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out throwing them quite away.</p>
            <p>For the fault was not there, but in themſelves: who came to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of holy things, with unprepared minds.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64584:6"/>Now for the eſtabliſhing of this Truth, that the people were not then, and therefore ought not now to be, debarred the liberty of reading the holy Books, (which God our Saviour hath left unto his Church, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Inheritance) you may be pleaſed to weigh theſe things following: which will fully ſettle your minds in this perſwaſion.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the ancient People of God, the Jews, were not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but required by God himſelf to be ſo converſant in the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and ſo well acquainted with it, as to be able to teach their Children God's Commandments: and for that end, <hi>to talk of them when they ſate in their houſes, or walkt by the way, when they lay down, and when they roſe up; nay, to write them upon the doors of their houſes, and on their gates;</hi> that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they went out or came in, they might have them before their eyes, and be put in mind of them,
<hi>Deut.</hi> VI. 6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64584:6"/>This the Lawgiver thought a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great importance, that a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after, in the very ſame Book, he enjoyns it over again; for fear they ſhould neglect it, <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> 18, 19, 20. For <hi>the very Root and foundation</hi> (as their Maſters ſpeak) <hi>upon which all the precepts depend, is this precept of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law:</hi> which no man can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine how they ſhould do, to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as
<hi>Moſes</hi> requires; unleſs they had the benefit of looking into the Book of the Law as often as they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>Of which that they might be put in mind, he took care alſo that the Law ſhould be read to them publickly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sabbath day: whereby likewiſe, they that could not read (if there were any ſuch among them) might be aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to inform their Children, by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Word read unto them, in their own language.</p>
               <p>For this is certain, that in the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues,</hi> where they met, not for the Ceremonial Worſhip of God (which was performed only at the Temple) but for his Moral Service, <hi>Moſes had thoſe that preached him</hi> (or pronounced<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64584:7"/>his Law with a loud voice)
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>from ancient ages or generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; being read in the Synagogues every Sabbath day.</hi> They are the words of St. <hi>James,</hi> in the firſt Chriſtian Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, XV.
<hi>Acts</hi> 21. Where <hi>Grotius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that it is believed,
<hi>Moſes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was the Author of this practice, which the Apoſtle affirms had been from <hi>old times, i. e.</hi> from the time of the giving of the Law. And ſo <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> expreſly writes in his ſecond Book againſt <hi>Appion:</hi> where he ſhews how <hi>Moſes</hi> propounded to the Jews, the <hi>moſt excellent and the moſt neceſſary of all other Learning,</hi> viz. <hi>the Law: not by letting them hear it once, or twice, or thrice; but every ſeventh day, laying aſide their other works, he commanded them to aſſemble together, for the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law, and to learn it through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and exactly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which end his <hi>Five Books</hi> were anciently divided into ſo many Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as there are weeks in the year: that the whole, by reading one Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every week, might be read over once in a year, ending at the Feaſt of Tabernacles. At which Feaſt, in the<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64584:7"/>Solemnity of the year of Releaſe (which was correſpondent to the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, becauſe it was the ſeventh of years, as that was of days) <hi>Moſes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that there ſhould be a more General Aſſembly of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> called to appear before the Lord their God; that the Law might be read to men, women, and children, and they might <hi>hear and learn, and fear the Lord their God, and obſerve to do all the words of this Law;</hi> as he ſpeaks XXXI.
<hi>Deut.</hi> 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Where <hi>Moſes</hi> declaring what God had commanded him about this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Hebrew Doctors underſtand thoſe words (<hi>v.</hi>
11.) <hi>Thou ſhalt read this Law before all Iſrael, in their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to be the Command of God to <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, requiring him, as he did the Elders and Prieſts under him, to read the Law at this great Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as the Ordinary Levites did eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sabbath day. And thence they, conſequently enough, conclude, that <hi>Joſhua</hi> after his time, and the <hi>Judges,</hi> and the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in ſucceeding Ages, were bound to read publickly in this great Aſſembly, to as many as<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64584:8"/>the largeſt Court of the Temple would hold, the principal things in the Book of <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> that the people might be moved to have an higher eſteem of their Law, and more reverently attend unto it. For it was of mighty force to excite the people to Religion, when the chief Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Nation, not only owned it, but commended it unto them.</p>
               <p>And becauſe all <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not be contained in that Court of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, therefore while the King was thus reading there; the
<hi>Levites,</hi> who were ſpecially appointed for this work, did the ſame in the City of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> after notice had been given of their intention, by a ſolemn ſound of Trumpets.</p>
               <p>Thus care was taken, that what he had enjoyned, <hi>Chap.</hi> VI. 7. ſhould not be neglected. For if they did forget to <hi>whet</hi> the Law (as the word there ſignifies) upon their Childrens minds, they themſelves were excited and whetted to their duty, by the ſound of the Trumpets, by this ſolemn Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, by the Royal Majeſty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to awaken their attention,<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64584:8"/>and by his Authority preſſing the Laws of God upon their Conſciences.</p>
               <p>This was the conſtant work alſo, it might be ſhown, of the
<hi>Prophets;</hi> out of whoſe Books, there were Leſſons alſo added in after-times; to be read together with thoſe out of the Law of
<hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ancient this was, we do not certainly know: for ſome derive it from the times of <hi>Ezra;</hi> others think it began after the Perſecution by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus Epiphanes.</hi> Who forbidding the reading of the Law in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, they choſe ſome portion out of the Prophetical Books (as near to the ſenſe of that Section, which ſhould have been read out of the Law, as could be found) to be read in its ſtead: which when that Perſecution was over, they thought not fit to lay aſide, but continued the reading of them both. But, however that be, this is a known truth, That when our Lord himſelf came, and, as his cuſtom was, went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and ſtood up to read, He took a Leſſon out of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> for the ſubject of his firſt Sermon at
<hi>Nazareth,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64584:9"/>IV. <hi>Luke</hi> 16, 17. And that it was,
<hi>after the reading of the Law and of the Prophets,</hi> that St.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſtood up and preached to the Jews at <hi>Antioch,</hi> XIII.
<hi>Acts</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>From which Examples, the cuſtom of reading two Leſſons, one out of the Old Teſtament, and another out of the New, was very early taken up by Chriſtians in their holy Aſſemblies: and continued ſo long in the Church, it appears by <hi>Iſidore,</hi> and <hi>Gratian,</hi> that it was moſt worthily reſtored by our Learned and Pious Reformers, whoſe ſtudy it was, to form ſuch an Order of Divine Service, as was moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Primitive Patterns.</p>
               <p>Which publick Reading was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to hinder their private; but to ſtir them up unto it. Inſomuch that it is a Maxim among the
<hi>Hebrews,</hi> That although a man had heard the Law read in the publick Aſſemblies on the Sabbath, yet he was bound alſo to read himſelf, the
<hi>Paraſcha</hi> or Section appointed for that Week. For this is the Character which <hi>David</hi> gives of that Bleſſed man, who walks not in the way of the ungodly, <hi>His delight<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64584:9"/>is in the Law of the Lord, and in his Law doth he meditate day and night, Pſal.</hi> I. 2. That is, ſaith the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, under the name of St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> reads the Scripture perpetually, that he may do the things contained therein. And thus
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> calls upon them, in after Ages, ſaying, <hi>Seek ye out the Book of the Lord, and read, no one of theſe ſhall fail,</hi> &amp;c. That is, when you ſhall hereafter ſee ſome of theſe things fulfilled, get a Copy of the Prophetical Books, if you want one, ſeek it diligently (as the word denotes) till you find it, and read; and you ſhall ſee that there is not one word of what I have ſaid, that is not come to paſs: but events ſhall exactly anſwer to theſe predictions.</p>
               <p>And it is well known that <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, in the very beginning, took particular care that the King ſhould be furniſhed with a Copy of the Law, and keep it by him, that he might <hi>read therein all the days of his life, and learn to fear the Lord his God, and to keep all the words of this Law, and theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, to do them,</hi> XVII. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18,
19. Nay, the more to imprint the words<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64584:10"/>of this Book upon his mind, the Law enjoyns this as a duty belonging to the King himſelf, ſaying,
<hi>He ſhall write him a Copy of this Law in a Book, out of that which is before the Prieſts the Levites.</hi> Which, though ſome are pleaſed to think a Priviledge indulged only to the King, the Jews (who are willing enough to excuſe themſelves from ſuch laborious things) conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm, that every private man was bound to do the ſame; and that though the King had done it before (as others were obliged to do) yet being exalted to the Throne, he was bound to do it over again, out of the moſt authentick Records; that it might be the more imprinted on his mind, and work in him a greater reverence thereof.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Maimonides</hi> grounds upon thoſe words, XXXI.
<hi>Deut.</hi> 19. which concern them all; <hi>Now therefore write ye this Song for you;</hi> as if he had ſaid, Write the Law for your ſelves, of which this Song is a part; for they were not wont to write the Law by parcels.</p>
               <p>Wherein perhaps they go too far; but there is little doubt to be made,<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64584:10"/>that pious Kings took care the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould be acquainted with the Law, as well as themſelves: imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that pious Prince
<hi>Joſiah,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long forgetfulneſs of the Holy Scriptures, having a Copy of the Law brought to him, which was found in the Temple, not only cauſed it to be read in the ears of the people; but (as the Jews, with great reaſon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm) commanded the Prieſts and Scribes to write Copies of it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them to the people. For how ſhould they be able to perform the words of the Covenantwritten in that Book, unto which <hi>Joſiah</hi> ingaged them (2 <hi>Kings</hi> XXIII. 2, 3.) unleſs they knew them? And how ſhould they know them more than they had done formerly, if they did only once bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear them? Which might give them ſome preſent ſenſe of their duty, but could not be remembred, unleſs they had the words they were to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, conſtantly before their eyes.</p>
               <p>There might much more be added on this ſubject, but this is ſufficient to introduce what follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64584:11"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>THAT what was thus enjoyned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and practiſed by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Jews, our <hi>Saviour</hi> confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Command, or, at leaſt, by his approbation; ſaying, V. <hi>John</hi> 39. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternal life: and they are they which teſtifie of me.</hi> Some indeed tranſlate the words thus, <hi>Ye ſearch the Scriptures, for in them,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo they are a plain acknowledgement of what was then in uſe; nay, an approbation, if not commendation, of their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, in turning over the holy Books; wherein they hoped to find ſo great a Treaſure as Eternal life. But if they be rendred as we, and as many of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves tranſlate them,
<hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> then they are a Command; wherein our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour requires what <hi>Moſes</hi> had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, and charges them not to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this duty of making a diligent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the meaning of the holy Writings; for there they would find plain teſtimonies concerning the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64584:11"/>and be ſatisfied that he was the Chriſt whom they expected.</p>
               <p>And I cannot ſee how this Precept may be ſafely diſobeyed. But as our Lord in the Parable of the Rich man and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> XVI.
<hi>Luke</hi> 29. brings in <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſending the Rich mans Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren unto <hi>Moſes and the Prophets</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> to their Writings, for they themſelves were dead and gone) for their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; from whom they might learn enough to keep them from coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that place of Torment: So we, in like manner, ought to tell men, if they will know how to be ſaved, they muſt repair to Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; and out of the Goſpel, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Inſtructions, learn the way to Heaven, and how to eſcape Eternal damnation.</p>
               <p>For there can be no good reaſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, why the Jews ſhould be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nay commanded to read <hi>Moſes</hi> and the
<hi>Prophets,</hi> and we not be allowed, but forbidden, to read the words of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> For we are as much concerned, or rather more, in theſe, as they were in them: and they are not harder to be underſtood by us,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64584:12"/>than the old Scriptures were by them: we have the ſame means, the ſame helps that they had, if not far better; to proſit by them, and to <hi>grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore it is no fault in our Preachers now, but an honeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their duty, to ſay to their people, as
<hi>Origen</hi> doth to his, in his ſecond Homily upon <hi>Iſaiah, Would to God we did all practiſe that which is written, Search the Scriptures.</hi> And as St. <hi>Baſil</hi> (in his Second Book of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, <hi>Cap.</hi>
4.) <hi>Let us obey our Lord who ſaith, Search the Scriptures: and let us imitate the Apoſtles, who inquired of the Lord himſelf, the interpretation of his own words; learning the truth and wholeſomneſs of what He ſaith in one place, by what He ſpeaks in another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So far were theſe great and Holy men, from diſcountenancing the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Scriptures; that they moſt earneſtly preſs every body to it, as I ſhall ſhow more fully before I have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64584:12"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>LET us now further conſider, that the Apoſtles of our Lord were concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that what they wrote, concerning the Chriſtian Doctrine, ſhould be read not only by the Elders of the Church, to whom their Writings were direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but be communicated to all the Members thereof, who were under their Inſtruction.</p>
               <p>This appears from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s moſt ſolemn Charge, in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that it ſhould be
<hi>read to all the holy Brethren,</hi> 1. v. 27. Who ſhould read it to them, but the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church? Who, no doubt, firſt received it; but were not to keep it to themſelves, but impart it to the whole Community. And if they read it to the whole Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we cannot think they refuſed to give Copies of it to them, if any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it, that they might read it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Or rather they took care to diſperſe this Letter of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, among their Flock; as they did alſo ſend it to other Churches, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64584:13"/>by it became common to the whole Chriſtian World</p>
               <p>And it was a matter of ſuch great importance, that all the people ſhould be acquainted with his ſenſe, that his <hi>Charge</hi> is in the form of an <hi>Adjuration. That if they neglected him, the Command ſhould be obeyed, for the Adjuration ſake. For Adjurations were dreadful to the ancient Chriſtians, though now, alas (wo be to us) they are little regarded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are words of <hi>Theophylact.</hi> And to the ſame effect
<hi>Theodoret</hi> gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>He adds an Adjuration, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that all might have the profit of the reading this Epiſtle. For perhaps other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, they that first received it, might not have given it unto all.</hi> As much as to ſay, He was afraid leſt the Epiſtle ſhould be ſuppreſſed, and read but by few: and therefore he requires them, for the love of God, and as they hoped for mercy from our Lord, that it ſhould be read unto all. Which teaches us, that the Word of God ought not to be concealed from the pooreſt Members of the Church; who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it, as much as the greateſt: And that if the Apoſtle were now<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64584:13"/>alive, and ſhould write to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, we may be confident, he would be more earneſt, if it be poſſible, in this matter: <hi>graviore conteſtatione ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurans,</hi> &amp;c. (as <hi>Muſculus</hi> writes) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding greater weight o his Adjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and beſeeching, nay, charging the Governours of the Churches (who now with all their might oppoſe the peoples reading of his Epiſtles) that as they expected the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was the Witneſs of what he ſaid, and would be their Judge, they would take care that all his words ſhould be diligently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the Faithful.</p>
               <p>It may not be amiſs to take notice, that to the ſame purpoſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> writes alſo in his Epiſtle to the
<hi>Coloſſians</hi> IV. 16. where he commands that this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle being read among them in that Church, they ſhould take care to have it read in that of <hi>Laodicea</hi> (by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is, a Copy of it to them) and the
<hi>Coloſſians</hi> on the other ſide, ſhould read the Epiſtle of the
<hi>Laodiceans:</hi> that is, the Epiſtle which he had ſent to that Church, as ſome (<hi>Theophylact</hi> obſerves) anciently underſtood it; or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64584:14"/>the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> which was written by him (as others, he ſaith, obſerve) from <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are plain demonſtrations, that the Writings of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were intended to be the common portion of all God's people, as thoſe of the Old had always been.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>AND thus I ſhall now proceed to ſhow they underſtood it: by repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that reading of the Scriptures was lookt upon as a Duty, and carefully practiſed by pious people, according to the forenamed injunction of our Bleſſed Lord, and the ſolemn obteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtle. For the ſame Apoſtle tells us, that his Son <hi>Timothy</hi> from his infancy had known the Holy Scriptures; which will not now be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the Roman Church to grown Chriſtians, without a ſpecial licence: no not to
<hi>Regulars,</hi> as they call them; whoſe whole buſineſs it is to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, but may not have any part of the Bible, in their own Language, without a faculty from their Superiors.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64584:14"/>Read 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> III. 15. and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it with the <hi>fifth</hi> verſe of the <hi>firſt</hi> Chapter, you will ſind that he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this early knowledge he had of the Scriptures, from his Grandmother and Mother (for his Father was not a
<hi>Jew,</hi> but a <hi>Greek</hi>) and therefore they were not ignorant in the Scriptures: but had made it their buſineſs to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them ſo well, that they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, according to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to teach them their Children.</p>
               <p>Which they began to do, ſaith the Apoſtle,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from their cradles, as we ſpeak in our Language: that is, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> admirably explains it,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt indication that they have any perception of other things. For ſo he writes in the Book before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>If any man ask any one of our Nation concerning the Laws, he will tell him all things more readily than his own name: for learning them ſtraightway, as ſoon as we come to have any knowledge of things, we retain them deeply ingraven upon our minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> alſo diſcourſe; <hi>at five years old they put their Children<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64584:15"/>to the Bible.</hi> Whereby they arrive at ſuch a proficiency, that in theſe latter Ages they have been able to tell any thing that is there. So <hi>Ribera</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Jeſuit relates in his Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon V. <hi>Micah</hi> 2.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">I knew a Jew, ſaith he, at <hi>Salamanca,</hi> who was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently unlearned, of whom when I inquired (in the Spaniſh Language, becauſe he underſtood no Latine) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeveral things, both in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical and in the Prophetical Books, he ſtopt me immediately, upon the firſt mention of them, from proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further: and repeated them all himſelf, without Book, in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Tongue. Which I relating to another Jew who was become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, he told me it was no wonder; for they committed all theſe things to memory from their Childhood.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Which may very well put thoſe Chriſtians to the bluſh, who are as careful and vigilant to keep not only their Children and Youth, but Elder people alſo from reading the Holy Scriptures, as the Jews are to bring them into acquaintance with them.</p>
               <p>And it is the more ſhameful, becauſe<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64584:15"/>even the <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> that is, they of other Nations, who embraced the Jewiſh Religion, were allowed this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, no leſs than the natural Jews themſelves. Which is apparent in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Eunuch</hi> belonging to the Queen of <hi>Ethiopia:</hi> whom St. <hi>Philip</hi> found (VIII. <hi>Acts</hi> 28.) reading the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as he was in his journey home-ward from <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> agreeable to the Precept of the Law before mentioned, that the Divine Writings ſhould be their Companions when they walkt on the way, as well as when they were within doors.</p>
               <p>This Eunuch was a man of a ſtrange Country, bred up in the Court of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia;</hi> which was the ſofteſt, they ſay, and moſt effeminate of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: yet, being converted to the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Religion, he had ſo much care of his Soul, as to read the Prophetical Books, the hardeſt of all the old Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. The ſenſe of which, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to
<hi>Philip,</hi> he did not underſtand: but that did not hinder his reading them. And becauſe he read them with a pious mind, God ſent him an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter: who improved his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64584:16"/>and advanced him from a Jew to be a Chriſtian: clothing the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> expreſſeth it, with the Snow-like fleece of the immaculate Lamb.</p>
               <p>Which that great Man juſtly alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as an Argument, why every one ſhould read the Scriptures, though they do not underſtand every thing that they read. If they do it honeſtly and piouſly, how do we know, ſaith he, but that they may fare as well as the Eunuch did: who felt his heart touched, in the reading, by the Spirit of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>CERTAIN it is, you may further obſerve, that this was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed in the firſt and beſt times of Chriſtianity, but it was accounted a noble quality in thoſe, who were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly converſant in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. As they of the City of <hi>Beraea</hi> may teach us: who hearing St. <hi>Paul</hi> preach that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the Chriſt, which he confirmed no doubt out of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, did not preſently reject what
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64584:16"/>he ſaid, becauſe it croſſed their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as a neighbouring City had done; but <hi>were more noble</hi> (ſaith the Text, XVII. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.) or better bred, <hi>than thoſe of</hi> Theſſalonica; <hi>ſearching the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo.</hi> Which is ſo far from being cenſured as a piece of preſumption, that God bleſſed theſe pious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and gave them a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as a reward of their ſearch into the Scriptures: according as it there follows, <hi>therefore many of them believed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus St. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo, in this very Epiſtle (<hi>Chap. I.</hi> 19.) commends his Country-men; who attentively read and conſidered the Prophetical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of Prophecy, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The plaineſt meaning of which words, to me, ſeems to be this;
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">That it was a laudable and praiſe-worthy thing in thoſe Jewiſh Converts to whom he writes (who as yet were but weak in the Faith) that they did<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64584:17"/>
                     <hi>give heed</hi> to the Writings of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Prophets; which they took to be the ſureſt ground of their Faith: for in them they would ſind the Lord Jeſus plainly deſcrihed, if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared what the Apoſtles preached with that which they foretold, as the <hi>Beraeans</hi> did. Thoſe Writings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of the Prophets, did but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely treat of Chriſt, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the diſcoveries of him in the Goſpel, and the Apoſtolical Writings (which he compares to the <hi>Day-ſtar,</hi> and the old Prophets but to a <hi>Candle ſhining in a dark place</hi>) yet the one would lead them to the other; and by taking attentive heed to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Writings, they would in time find the <hi>day dawn,</hi> and the <hi>Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar ariſe in their hearts:</hi> that is, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive by degrees at clearer demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a fuller and brighter know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſtian Truths, delivered by our Saviour and his Apoſtles: who being the <hi>Light of the World,</hi> gave light even to the ancient Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this particular; they were ſo far from diſcouraging any<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64584:17"/>Chriſtians, in their reading the Holy Scriptures, that they commend thoſe who read even the hardeſt Books a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Thoſe words are very remarkable, I. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this Prophecy; and keep thoſe things that are written therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which comfortable incouragement I do not ſee why we may not, with the greateſt ſatisfaction, apply to our ſelves now, as they did then, to quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us to read and hear the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein. For though we do not certainly underſtand every one of thoſe Prophecies; yet there are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of moſt excellent inſtructions and admonitions, incouragements and conſolations interſperſed throughout that Book: which make it ſit to be read by Chriſtian people for their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and ſupport. And we may likewiſe from hence take the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to argue in this manner: If a Bleſſedneſs be pronounced to thoſe that <hi>read or hear that Prophecy, and keep thoſe things that are written therein;</hi> then they cannot be accurſed, who for the ſame end read other holy Books,<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64584:18"/>where ſuch inſtructions and comforts are more plentifully, and plainly, and on purpoſe delivered: nor can they expect God's bleſſing who prohibit the reading even of thoſe eaſie and more familiar Scriptures, which are accommodated by the Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs to the moſt vulgar ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</p>
               <p>Every one ought to drink of theſe <hi>Fountains:</hi> nor would I forbid (ſaith <hi>Eraſmus</hi> very piouſly) thoſe that thirſt after Chriſtian knowledge, to read even thoſe Books, which are not ſo open, but like a <hi>Fountain ſealed up.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will reap this fruit at leaſt, that they will come more ſit to the hearing of Sermons, which touch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or allude to thoſe more obſcure paſſages. They will hear alſo thoſe things more willingly, of which they have already ſome knowledge: and underſtand thoſe things more eaſily, of which they have a ſmall taſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>AND there is the greater reaſon for it, becauſe the Holy Scriptures are<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64584:18"/>a conſiderable part of our compleat Spiritual Armour; without which we ſhall lie ſo open to the aſſaults of our Enemies, that it will very much haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard our Salvation. And why ſhould we be expoſed to any danger, when we may defend our ſelves by the uſe of thoſe weapons which God himſelf hath provided for us? Or how can they be Friends to our Souls, who would expoſe us by taking thoſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons out of our hands?</p>
               <p>Read the VI. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where the Apoſtle exhorting them to <hi>put on the whole Armour</hi> (or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Armour) <hi>of God, that they might be able to ſtand againſt all the wiles of the Devil;</hi> in the following Verſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerates the ſeveral parts of this Armour; and the laſt piece of it, but one, is (<hi>v.</hi> 17) <hi>the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is the Word of God.</hi> This ſhews that, as while we have Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to fight withal, and very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, ſubtil Enemies, we have need of all ſorts of Weapons that God hath furniſhed us withal for our defence; ſo we are not completely appointed for our defence, without
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64584:19"/>this weapon, <hi>the Word of God,</hi> no more than a Souldier is without his Sword. And therefore they who go about to deprive us of this leave us, in great part, naked to our Spiritual Enemies: By wreſting that weapon out of our hands, whereby we ſhould beat them off.</p>
               <p>There is not one of the Devils tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, ye may obſerve, (IV. St. <hi>Matth.</hi>) but our Saviour vanquiſhed it by this weapon: telling him, it is ſo and ſo written; and the Tempter had no more to ſay, nor knew what to oppoſe thereunto. And therefore our ſafety lies in the ſame Divine Armory of the Holy Scriptures: unto which we ought to have reſort upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and there furniſh our ſelves with ſuch holy Precepts, Examples, Promiſes, and Threatnings, as we may have ready at hand to oppoſe to every temptation.</p>
               <p>It is uſually ſaid, as I noted in the beginning, that men may wound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a Sword, as ſoon as their Enemies: and therefore it is not ſafe to let every body take this weapon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64584:19"/>But was not the Apoſtle as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of this as we? Were not the Holy Scriptures as liable to be perverted then, as now? And we by this reaſon ſhall leave neither Sun in Heaven, nor any good Creature here upon Earth (as a great Man of our own ſomewhere ſpeaks) for they have been all wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly abuſed to very ill purpoſes by evil men.</p>
               <p>And beſides this, it is not true that men may as ſoon hurt themſelves, as their Enemies, with this Sword. For who but mad men, or deſperate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, run that weapon into their own bodies, wherewith they ſhould defend their lives? And who but they that are diſtracted themſelves, will ſuppoſe the generality of Chriſtians to be ſuch a frantick fort of people, that they are not to be truſted with the means of their preſervation: but muſt have even the bread of life taken from them, for fear they ſurfeit of it?</p>
               <p>But this will be more fully anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hereafter: and that which I have next to repreſent to your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will give great ſatisfaction to it, which is this,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64584:20"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>THAT the greateſt Doctors in the Church have moſt earneſtly exhorted the people, with all the Rhetorick they could invent, to give themſelves lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for this holy imployment, of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> for inſtance, in a number of places, maintains theſe three Propoſitions, with an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary zeal, and paſſionate concern, to have them believed and practiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That all men, of whatſoever rank and condition they be, ought to read the Bible; not only at Church, but at home.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it is more neceſſary for a mere Lay-man, as we ſpeak, to read it, than it is for a Monk, or thoſe that are wholly ſequeſtred from the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That neither the obſcurity of the Scriptures, nor indeed any thing elſe, ought to be thought a ſufficient reaſon why men ſhould not read them.</p>
               <p n="1">I. For the firſt of theſe, [<hi>That all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64584:20"/>men, of whatſoever rank and condition they be, ſhould read the Scriptures</hi>] his words are very remarkable upon that place of St.
<hi>Paul,</hi> III. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly, in all wiſdom, teaching and admoniſhing one another,</hi> &amp;c. where he cries out with great vehemence,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Hearken to this as many of you as are men of the world, and have wives and children under your care; how he commands, even you especially, to read the Scriptures: and that net ſimply, nor by the bye, but with a great deal of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi> Which he preſſes, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the heavenly Treaſure here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with all other riches; and then returns to his Exhortation again, ſaying,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Hearken, I beſeech you, all ye that are Secular men: provide your ſelves with Bibles, the Medicines of your Souls. If not with the whole, yet at leaſt the New Teſtament; the Apoſtles, the Acts, the Goſpels, your perpetual Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. If any ſadneſs befal thee, look into theſe as into a Repoſitory or Shop of ſpiritual Remedies. Hence fetch conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in all doleful caſes; whether it be<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64584:21"/>any damage in thy goods, or it be death, or the loſs of ſervants. Or rather do not look into them; but take them all to thy ſelf; carry them about with thee in thy mind. This is the cauſe of all evils, not to know the Scriptures. We go to War without our Armour, without Weapons; how can we be ſafe? It is eaſie to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with theſe; but not without them. Do not throw all upon our ſhoulders. Ye are Sheep; but not irrational ones, but reaſonable: and many things the Apoſtle lays upon you. Who ought to learn of us: and then your wives and your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought to learn of you. But you would leave all to us: which gives us no ſmall trouble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſame purpoſe he diſcourſes in other places of his works; and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it by ſuch arguments as theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> that every man hath need of ſuch inſtruments as belong to his art. A <hi>Black-ſmith</hi> (ſaith he in his third Sermon upon <hi>Lazarus</hi>) <hi>or Gold-ſmith cannot work without their Anvil, their Hammer and their Tongs, and ſuch like Tools: which they will by no means part withall, though they ſuffer hunger and thirſt; becauſe then they give up <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64584:21"/>their trade, and all means of their ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is gone: and even juſt ſo ought we to be diſpoſed; who can no more go to work, without the Apoſtolical and Prophetical Writings, and other divinely inſpired Scriptures, than they without thoſe Tools. For as by thoſe Inſtruments they form and faſhion all the Veſſels they take in hand: So we by theſe, hammer, as I may ſay, our own Souls, amending and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming all that is amiſs, renewing what is decayed, nay, making our ſelves quite other Men. For here is the difference between us and them: They ſhew their art only in the outward figure of a thing (for they cannot alter the matter of it; by turning Silver, for inſtance into Gold) but we, by theſe Divine Inſtruments, may do a great deal more; turn an Earthen Veſſel, into a Golden; a Veſſel unto Honour, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and meet for the Maſters uſe, and prepared unto every good Work. Let us not neglect therefore the getting of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: Nor let us dig for Gold, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther treaſure up theſe Spiritual Books. For the more Gold we have, the more hurt it may do us: But Bibles if we get, they will do thoſe that have them a great deal of good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:64584:22"/>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> He preſſes this, by this further conſideration, that as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> would have us, <hi>let the Word of Chriſt dwell in us richly</hi> and abundantly: ſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> requires us <hi>to be ready always to give an anſwer to every man, that asketh us a reaſon of the hope that is in us.</hi> 1. Pet.
<hi>III.</hi> 15. <hi>Now what ſay our idle People, more lazy than Drones, to this? They comfort themſelves with thoſe words in the</hi> Proverbs,
<hi>Bleſſed is the ſimple Soul. For this is the cauſe of all our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, that many do not underſtand how to produce the Teſtimonies of the Scriptures to the purpoſe. For the Wiſe Man by the Simple doth not there mean, an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant man, that underſtand nothing; but a harmleſs man, that works no evil, but hath skill only to do goad.</hi> Thus he diſcourſes in his XVII Homily upon S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel: Where he ſhews it is an unpardonable neglect, not to be able out of the Holy Scriptures, to repel the aſſaults of Gentile Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. <hi>For it is a moſt abſurd thing, that every Phyſician ſhould be able to give an exact account of his art; nay a Currier or Weaver, or any other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt can do the ſame; only he that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64584:22"/>a Chriſtian, cannot give an account of his own Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As every man is bound to give a reaſon of his Faith; ſo he is bound to take care of his Souls pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in Vertue and Goodneſs: Which he cannot do, unleſs he be converſant in the Holy Writings. <hi>For what ſenſible Food is to the increaſe of bodily ſtrength, that the reading of the Scriptures is to the Soul. It is a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Nouriſhment; and renders the Soul ſtronger, more conſtant, and more philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical: not ſuffering it to be carried away with abſurd imaginations; but making it pure and lightſome, gives it wings to carry it up to Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Much more to the ſame purpoſe he ſpeaks in his XXIX Homily upon <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis:</hi> and begins the XXXV. in this manner. <hi>Great is the good, my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, of skill in the Divine Writings. For this makes a Philoſophical Soul</hi> (that is, inſtructs it in all manner of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue)
<hi>this forms a man to be acceptable: this makes him mind none of theſe things preſent, but to have his mind alwayes in the other Life: that looking at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence our Lord will give us, we may<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64584:23"/>do all that He would have us, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the labours of Vertue with great chearfulneſs. For from thence we may exactly learn the Providence of God's ſpeedy ſuccour and help; the Fortitude of the Righteous; the Goodneſs of our Lord; the Greatneſs of his Rewards. From thence we may be excited to a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous imitation of the Chriſtian Vertue of brave men: that we may not flag in the Combates of Vertue; but be confident and aſſured in the Divine Promiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to paſs. Therefore let us, I beſeech you, with great diligence apply our ſelves to the reading of holy Writings: for thereby we ſhall be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Divine knowledge, if we fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently make them our ſtudy: it being impoſſible that he ſhould be neglected by God, who with earneſt diligence and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent deſire, imploys himſelf in theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things; but, if no man can be found to teach us, the Lord himſelf will come from above into our hearts, and inlighten our minds, and ſhine into our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and reveal thoſe things that are hidden, and inſtruct us in thoſe things wherein we are ignorant; provided we will contribute all that lies in us to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64584:23"/>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> This he illuſtrates by the Example of the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> in the VIII. of the <hi>Acts:</hi> whom he magnifies in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of his Works (as I ſhall have occaſion to obſerve) upon ſeveral accounts, belonging to this matter: particularly here, for not neglecting to read the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> though he himſelf was a Barbarian, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant what the Prophet ſaid: but
<hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did what he could, and with all the diligence he was able, he obtained a Guide from God. Conſider here, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, how beneficial it was to this man, that he did not omit reading; no, though he was in a journey, on the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Let thoſe hearken to this, who will not do ſo much at home: but look upon this as a by-buſineſs, becauſe they coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit with a wife, or are liſted Souldiers, and have the care of children, and muſt look after their ſervants, and have a great deal of buſineſs in the World; which they imagine ſufficiently excuſes them from troubling themſelves with reading the Holy Script res.</hi> For ſee here all this confuted in this Barbarian, a man of buſineſs, and in his journey, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who was ſo ſtudious and intent upon his<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64584:24"/>reading, that nothing could divert him from it; as he proceeds to ſhow in that <hi>Homily</hi> with a great deal of Eloquence; which will be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently alledged under ſome of the other general Heads. I only obſerve one thing more under this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That he urges this obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they had upon them to read the Holy Scriptures, from this Argument, That otherwiſe they would not be able to inſtruct their Children and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: as he tells them they were bound to do, from the forenamed Precept of St. <hi>Paul, Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly, in all wiſdom, teaching and admoniſhing one another in Pſalms,</hi> &amp;c. Obſerve, ſaith he, <hi>how the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle declines all that might deter them from this buſineſs. Becauſe there is great pains to be taken in the reading ſome Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and it is a laborious buſineſs to underſtand them; therefore he commends the Pſalms: that he might at once delight their minds, and make the labour eaſie to them. Now your Children are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Satanical Songs and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; like to thoſe who keep Victualling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and Dancing-maſters: but none<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64584:24"/>of them knows ſo much as one Pſalm. Hence all our miſchieſs: for like to the Soil in which the Plant is ſet, will be the fruit. Teach thy Children therefore to chant the Pſalms; thoſe that are full of Philoſophy. For Example, thoſe ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that teach temperance: or rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all, thoſe about avoiding ill compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with which the Book begins. For upon this ſcore the Prophet enters upon his work with this admonition: Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the way of the ungodly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and again,</hi> (26.4.) <hi>I have not ſat with vain perſons: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain</hi> (XV 4) <hi>in whoſe eyes a vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is contemned, but he honoureth them that fear the Lord. Like to theſe thou wilt find many more, concerning bridling the appetite of meat and drink, and all the pleaſures of the belly; concerning keeping the hands from theft; againſt covetouſneſs; and that riches are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor glory neither, nor all the reſt of like nature. If from a Child thou accuſtom him to theſe Notions, by little and little thou wilt advance him to ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer apprehenſions. For then he will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Hymns, which have nothing humane in them, but are things more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64584:25"/>For the heavenly Powers ſing Hymns, not Pſalms,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By which repeated Exhortations, it appears, theſe were not haſty thoughts, which on a ſudden ſprung up in him, when he was in the heat of his diſcourſe: but the deliberate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and ſetled ſenſe of his mind; which was highly concerned to bring all the people, committed unto his charge, to a more familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>This will ſtill more fully appear in the <hi>Second</hi> Propoſition which he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: and that is ſuch, as may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly put to ſhame the Doctrine of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church. For it is this,</p>
               <p n="2">II. That <hi>it is more neceſſary for a Lay-man to read the Scriptures, than for a Monk, or thoſe that are ſequeſtred from the World.</hi> To this purpoſe he diſcourſes in his ſecond Sermon upon St. <hi>Matthew: This is the plague that now infeſts us, and corrupts all; that you imagine the reading of the Scriptures belongs to Monks only, and not to you that have wives and children, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs: whereas it is more neceſſary<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64584:25"/>for you, than for them. For they that live in the World, being moſt expoſed to the danger of being wounded, have moſt need of medicines;</hi> to preſerve them, that is, or to cure them.</p>
               <p>Thus likewiſe in the third Sermon upon <hi>Lazarus</hi> before mentioned, he diſcourſes to this effect: <hi>Let no man tell me, I am ingaged in pleading Cauſes, the publick buſineſs lies upon me, I have a Trade, I muſt live by my handy work, I have a wife and family; in ſhort, I am a man of the World, and it is not for me to read the Scriptures: but for thoſe who have bid an adieu to it. What doſt thou ſay, man; is it not thy buſineſs to turn over the Scriptures, becauſe thou art diſtracted with worldly cares? For that very reaſon it is more thy buſineſs, than theirs. For they have leſs need of the defence of the Scriptures, than we have: who are toſſed in the midſt of the waves of buſineſs. They are, as it were, in the Haven; they are ſecure, and enjoy perfect tranquillity: it is we who fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in the midſt of the Sea; who are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, whether we will or no, to innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſins; and therefore have perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual need of the comfort and the aſſiſtance of the Holy Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64584:26"/>What can more effectually repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſenſe of the ancient Doctors, than this? unleſs it be what follows, out of the XXI. <hi>Homily</hi> upon <hi>Geneſis;</hi> upon thoſe words,
<hi>Noah begat three Sons. Let us not bring forth thoſe frigid words, I am a worldly man, I have a wife, the care of children lies upon me: as the manner of many is to excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when we bid them labour to be good, and apply their ſtudy to read the Holy Scriptures. That doth not belong to me, ſay they; have I renounced the World? am I a Monk? What doſt thou ſay, man? Doth this belong to Monks only to ſtudy in all things to pleaſe God, who would have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the Truth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us not deceive our ſelves; but the more we are intangled in ſuch kind of cares, let us ſo much the more carefully ſearch for a remedy, in the reading of the Holy Scriptures. Was not</hi> Noah <hi>and ſuch like good men, of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of which we are? and yet had not the benefit of thoſe helps and aſſiſtances that we enjoy. How can we then be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, who enjoy ſuch a Doctrine, who have obtained ſuch Grace, who have<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64584:26"/>helps from above, and have received the promiſes of ineffable good things; if we do not come to the meaſure of that Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, at which thoſe Patriarchs arrived? I beſeech you therefore again, that you would not only ſimply look into thoſe things which are contained in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; but that you would read them with attention: that by the profit we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them, we may at laſt, though we have been a long time about it, come to that degree of Vertue which God will approve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame he urges again, in the XXXV. <hi>Homily</hi> upon the ſame Book, from the Example of the Eunuch read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures in his Chariot: which he thus concludes. <hi>I have laid this Hiſtory before you, that we may not be aſhamed to imitate this Eunuch; nor neglect reading, no not in a journey. For this Barbarian alone may ſuffice for a Maſter to us all: both to thoſe that lead a private Country-life, and to thoſe who are liſted to ſerve in the Army, and to thoſe that live in the Court; and in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, to all men, and to women too, and to thoſe that live in Monaſteries alſo, that no time ſhould be thought unfit to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64584:27"/>reading of the Holy Oracles. For it is poſſible, not only within doors, but to thoſe who go to Market, that are in Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that fall into a great deal of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that are intangled in buſineſs, to be converſant in them: that doing what we can, we may meet with one to guide us. And what if we do not underſtand what we read? let us go it over again. For frequent meditation imprints things on the memory and oft-times what we could not underſtand to day, we may find out preſently when we read it again to morrow: the moſt gracious God inviſibly illuminating our underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which leads me to the laſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which he maintains, in Anſwer to all Objections that can be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt this Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That, <hi>as none ought to neglect reading, becauſe they are men of buſineſs ſo, they ought not to excuſe themſelves, becauſe they want Bibles; or becauſe the Scriptures are ſo obſcure, that they do not underſtand them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning buſineſs, you have heard already what he was wont to ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:64584:27"/> And concerning want of Bibles; he tells them, the rich cannot pretend this. And as for the poor, <hi>I would ask them,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this Queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have not all the tools belonging to their Trade. And ſince they can fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh themſelves with ſuch neceſſary imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, why they ſhould not judge it moſt abſurd to be wholly unprovided of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures: which are as neceſſary for their spiritual, as the other for their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſubſiſtence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to the greateſt Objection of all, <hi>the obſcurity of the Holy Scriptures,</hi> and that it is impoſſible to underſtand them, he anſwers very largely in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of his Works: particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in that <hi>Homily</hi> forenamed upon <hi>Geneſis XXXV.</hi> ſpeaking of the Eunuch of the Queen of <hi>Ethiopia. Who did not ſay, as many do now, I underſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of what I read; I cannot dive into the depth of theſe Scriptures; to what purpoſe ſhould I take all this pains and tire my ſelf in vain, by reading: when I have none to lead me into the meaning? No ſuch thought was entertained by him, who was a Barbarian in his language, but a Philoſopher in his mind: and rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64584:28"/>he ſhould not be deſpiſed, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive help from above, if, doing all that lay in his power, he continued reading the Holy Scriptures. And therefore the moſt Gracious Lord of all, ſeeing his ardent deſire, did not overlook him, nor left him unprovided: but ſtraightway ſent him a Maſter to inform him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See here the Wiſdom of God, how He expected till he firſt did what he could; and then He manifeſted his own power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aid. Becauſe he prepared himſelf, the beſt he was able, an Angel of the Lord was ſent to</hi> Philip, <hi>that he might do the reſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But this Argument he proſecutes moſt largely, in his
<hi>Third</hi> Sermon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Lazarus. Where,</hi> firſt of all he ſays,
<hi>a man cannot look into the Holy Scriptures, but he muſt be made better: God converſing with him there in thoſe Writings: ſo that though he do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what he reads, yet his mind will be much purified by reading:</hi> by a holy ſenſe of God, he means, upon whom his mind is fixed, as ſpeaking to him.</p>
               <p>But immediately he further adds, that what is objected, is not true of all Scriptures: ſome being ſo plain,<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64584:28"/>
                  <hi>that it is impoſſible to be without under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all things whatſoever, that we read there. For the Grace of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, on purpoſe ordered theſe Books to be compoſed by Publicans, by Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, by Tent-makers, by Shepherds, and ſuch like mean and unlearned men, that none of the common people might flee to this Pretence; but the things that are there written, might be intelligible to all. That the Handicrafts-men, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and the poor old Women, and the moſt illiterate of all mankind, might be gainers, and profit by the hearing of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what they deſigned they effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; <hi>For to whom are not all things in the Goſpel manifeſt and clear? Who is there that reads theſe words, Bleſſed are the meek, bleſſed are the merciful, bleſſed are the pure in heart, and the like, that needs any other Teacher to inſtruct him, what it is that is ſaid? And are not all things that relate to ſigns and wonders, and the Hiſtory of Chriſt, clear and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be underſtood of all? Theſe obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are but a cover and pretext under which men hide their ſloth and idleneſs</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which further appears from the<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64584:29"/>temper of thoſe men, that from the beginning were counted worthy <hi>of the Grace of the Spirit: who compoſed all things, not as they without the Pale of the Church, for Oſtentation, and their own Vain-glories ſake, but for the Salvation of thoſe that heard them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Heathen Philoſophers indeed, and Orators, and other Writers, not ſeeking the common good of all, but aiming at the making themſelves admired, when they ſaid any profitable thing, made it difficult to be underſtood, and wrapt it up in ſome obſcurity: But the Apoſtles and Prophets did all quite contrary, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all plain and clear, as the common Teachers of the whole World; that every one might be able, of himſelf, to learn, by the bare reading only, ſuch neceſſary things as thoſe now mentioned. Which the Prophet foreſhewed when he ſaid, they ſhall all be taught of God. And every man ſhall not ſay to his Neighbour know the Lord; for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt. And ſo St.</hi> Paul, <hi>I came not to you in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Speech, or of Wiſdom, ſhowing you the Myſteries of God. And again, my Speech and my Preaching was not in<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64584:29"/>the enticing words of man's Wiſdom: but in the demonſtration of the Spirit and of Power. And again, we ſpeak Wiſdom among them that are perfect; yet not the Wiſdom of this World, nor of the Princes of this World, that come to nought,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And <hi>laſtly,</hi> he proves this from the intention for which they wrote theſe Books: which was that all might find a remedy here of whatſoever troubled them. This he admirably proſecutes in theſe words, becauſe thou art en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in Family-affairs and a world of buſineſs, therefore thou haſt the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter need of more Medicines. <hi>For not only thy Wife provokes thee, but thy Child makes thee ſad, and thy Servant angers thee, and thy Enemy deviſeth miſchief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and thy Friend envies thee, and thy Neighbour does thee damage, and thy Fellow-ſouldier ſupplants thee: Nay perhaps, He that ſits in judgment threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens thee, and Poverty makes thee ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, and the Running away of thy Servants fetches tears from thy Eyes: in ſhort, either Prosperity puffs thee up; or Adverſity pinches thee ſore, and makes thee ſhrink. There are many occaſions<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64584:30"/>of Anger, many of Thoughtfulneſs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Sadneſs and Sorrow; and many alſo of Vain-glory and ſenſlleſs Pride: Straits and Dificulties encompaſs us on every ſide, and a thouſand Darts from all ſides come flying at us. And therefore we have perpetual need of that Panoply (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Armour) which is to be ſetcht out of the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A great deal more there follows, which I ſhall not tranſcribe, to ſhew what a neceſſity there is of theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Remedies to heal the wounds we receive; or rather to keep off the blow that gives them, and to beat back the fiery Darts of the Devil, by a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent reading of the Holy Scriptures: and concludes thus,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. For <hi>it cannot be, it is impoſſible that any man ſhould be ſaved, that enjoyes not continually the Benefit of Spiritual Reading.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But after he hath thus anſwered the Objection about the obſcurity of the Scriptures, by denying it to be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether true: He proceeds further to ſhew, that granting it to be true, they are not therefore to be laid aſide, and not to be read by us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64584:30"/>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe by often reading, that which is obſcure may become plain. So he diſcourſes in the often named Sermon upon <hi>Lazarus. Doſt thou not underſtand what is in theſe Books? No, how ſhouldſt thou underſtand when thou wilt not ſo much as look into them? Take the Bible into thy hand read the whole Hiſtory; and retaining what is plain and intelligible, read what is obſcure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, over and over again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Suppoſe thou canſt not with frequent reading find out the ſenſe: then go to one that is wiſer than thy ſelf: come to the Teacher and Inſtructer, as a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to his Maſter: Communicate with him concerning the things that are ſpoken: Demonſtrate a great diligence and deſire to learn: and if God ſee this forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and readineſs of mind in thee, He will not overlook thy watchfulneſs, and ſollicitous care; but if no man can be found to teach thee, He will reveal his mind Himſelf to thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This he explains by the example often already named, ſaying,
<hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Eunuch of the Queen of</hi> Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia, <hi>who being a Barbarian and ingaged in a thouſand cares, and ſurrounded
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64584:31"/>with abundance of buſineſs, and did not underſtand what he read, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding continued reading as he ſate in his Chariot. If he ſhewed ſuch diligence upon the High-way, conſider what kind of man he was at home. If he would not ſuffer the time of his travel to paſs away without reading, how much more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, may we well think, he was when he ſate in his Houſe? If when he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not what he read, he would not omit reading; how much more did he uſe it, after he had learnt ſomething? For that he did not underſtand what he read, his anſwer to</hi> Philip <hi>ſhews, when he ask'd him, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeſt thou what thou read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt? He did not bluſh, nor was aſhamed to confeſs his Ignorance; but ſaid, how can I, unleſs I had ſome body to guide me? Becauſe therefore he thus imployed his time in reading, when he had none to guide him; therefore ſtraightway one was ſent to conduct and lead him. God ſaw his forwardneſs and accepted his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and preſently ſent him a Teacher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> Philip <hi>is not here preſent with me; to inſtruct me, when I read. True; but the Spirit which moved</hi> Philip <hi>is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Let us not, my beloved, deſpiſe<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64584:31"/>our own Salvation. All theſe things were written for our Inſtruction; upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reading of the Scripure is a great ſecurity againſt Sin: and ignorance of them is a great precipice, a deep pit, or rather bottomleſs gulph: A manifeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying of Salvation, to know Nothing out of the Divine Laws. This hath both brought forth Hereſies; and led to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Manners. This hath turned all things topſy-turvy. For it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, utterly impoſſible, for any man to go away from reading the Holy Scriptures, without ſome fruit; if he read them with care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould tire my Reader, if I ſhould ſet down all that this Great and Holy man hath ſaid upon this ſubject. Which he preſſes, you ſee, with ſuch vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence; as if he thought it impoſſible for his people to be ſaved, unleſs they read the Holy Scriptures. So con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary was the Doctrine then, to what is now current in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: who teach, that people will rather indanger their Salvation, by the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
               <p>And one thing I cannot paſs by<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64584:32"/>without a particular Remark, before I have done with this. That he gives that very reaſon (in the words juſt now quoted) why the people ſhould read the Scriptures, which the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> give why they ſhould not read them, <hi>viz. the danger of running into Errours and Hereſies.</hi> Therefore, ſay they, the people ought not to read the Scriptures: no ſuch matter, ſaith he, but quite contrary, they will run into them, if they do not read them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From hence spring up myriads of evils, even from Ignorance of the Scriptures: from hence pernicious Hereſies, negligent Life, and corruption of Manners. For as they who are deſtitute of light, cannot make ſtraight paths: ſo ſuch as do not take along with them the light of God's Word, in many things neceſſarily offend and ſtumble, as walking in utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are his words in his XXXII. Sermon upon St. <hi>John.</hi> And in his VIII. Sermon upon the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> he makes a ſad complaint about the growth of one particular Hereſie; that of the <hi>Manichees:</hi> and tells his people, it was becauſe they neglected <pb n="55" facs="tcp:64584:32"/>the Scripture. <hi>For if we attended to them, we ſhould not only preſerve our ſelves from the deceit, but deliver others alſo that are deceived, and draw them out of the danger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is time to make an end of this, and therefore I ſhall only add theſe few memorable words of his, out of his ſecond Sermon upon St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> (that you may ſee how faithfully they follow the Fathers, who pretend to be wholly guided by them) <hi>If there be a greater ſin than that of not reading the Scriptures, it is this; to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that we need not read them,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>for theſe are words of a Satanical ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> the ſtudied invention of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
               <p>I have been the longer upon this Head, becauſe ſome are more moved by a great Authority, than by bare Reaſon. And I have alledged this Father's Authority alone, not for want of other (which are ready at hand in great abundance) but becauſe it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly very weighty; and as he is full and expreſs in his Judgment about this matter, ſo he intermixes his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64584:33"/>upon it, with many excellent Inſtructions.</p>
               <p>But if we had neither his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, nor any other to produce, there is one piece of Hiſtory remaining, which is ſufficient to ſatisfie any man in this matter. Which is, that it was the very Mark and Character of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to have a <hi>Bible;</hi> and of an
<hi>Apoſtate,</hi> to deliver his Bible to be burnt; when the Inquiſitors came to ſearch for it in times of Perſecution.</p>
               <p>As they did particularly in the Reign of <hi>Maxentius</hi> and of <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> when they ſought to deſtroy all <hi>Bibles,</hi> as the Foundation of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; which they thought would fall, when theſe Books were gone. And that <hi>Lay-men</hi> generally had Bibles, as well as <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and were guilty of this foul Crime of delivering them up to the Perſecutors, appears by <hi>Optatus</hi> in his firſt Book againſt <hi>Parmenio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid commemorem Laicos,</hi> &amp;c.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">What need I ſtand to mention the <hi>Lay-peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> who then had no Dignities in the Church, or many <hi>Miniſters</hi> (he means inferiour Officers) or <hi>Deacons</hi> in the third Order, or <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64584:33"/>Prieſtood, when the very Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, ſome Biſhops in thoſe times, <hi>impiouſly delivered up the Inſtruments of the Divine Law.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>He names ſeveral, and among the reſt <hi>Donatus.</hi> And the ſame we find in St. <hi>Auſtin, Epiſt.</hi> XLVIII. and CLXXI. and other places: Where he relates
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">how ſome delivered up the Holy Books to the Perſecutors; and others who did not, communicated with them that did: mixing with the Church <hi>TRADITOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M plebem congregatam,</hi> a whole Congregation of people that were <hi>Traditors.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſhows, that Bibles were then as common as they are now: and that S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s complaints were very juſt againſt thoſe, who were grown ſo cold and negligent in providing themſelves theſe Holy Books, as if they ſtill had been under Perſecution, and it were not ſafe to have them, now that they lived under Chriſtian Emperours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64584:34"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>BUT now let us hear what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon ſaith (as well as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the beſt Interpreters of them, ſuch great Lights as he now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) and that teaches us, that ſince the Holy Scriptures were written for the uſe and benefit of all, all ſhould have liberty to read them.</p>
               <p>They were written for all, it is plain; for that which they teach is the duty of all; that which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is the portion of all. And if any one ſay, it doth not therefore follow they ſhould be read by all, becauſe the people may be taught by others, without looking into the Scriptures themſelves; they render themſelves ſuſpected that they intend not to teach the people ſincerely what is written; but to eſtabliſh their own Authority, inſtead of that of the Divine Writings. For otherwiſe, why ſhould they not rather, when they pretend to teach others, bid them look into their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and there ſatisfie themſelves, that they do not abuſe them: aſſuring<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64584:34"/>them it is a faithful Tranſlation of God's Book, which they have in their hands; whoſe meaning it is their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to help them to underſtand?</p>
               <p>That is, why do they not imitate God himſelf? Who commanding his Prophet to proclaim him to be the only God among the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> and that the Gods which made not the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the Earth, ſhould periſh from the Earth, and from under theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, ordered him to do it in their own Language, that they might read and underſtand it, X. <hi>Jer.</hi> 11. Where, when all the reſt of the Book is <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> this Meſſage is delivered in the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Tongue. Which we may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look upon, as a <hi>Praeludium</hi> to the publiſhing of the Name of God among the Gentiles in their own Language, in the days of Chriſt. When, as <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> witneſſeth, the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets, were turned into the Language of the <hi>Romans, Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians, Perſians, Indians, Armenians, Scythians,</hi> and <hi>Sauromatans,</hi> and all the Languages that any other Nation uſed. And therefore why ſhould not we now have them in
<hi>Engliſh?</hi> And<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64584:35"/>having them, why ſhould not all read, that they may learn the way to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py here and eternally; and that they may be ſure they are not led into a wrong way: and abuſed by pretended Authority from God, who, perhaps, ſaith the quite contrary to what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in his Name?</p>
               <p>This is the Peoples Right; and it it their Duty to uſe it, as that Great Man S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (whoſe words let me ſet down once more) teaches his Church, upon 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> VII. in the concluſion of his XIII. Sermon. <hi>For how can we think it not to be abſurd, that having to deal in money-matters, men will not truſt to others; but the Counters are brought out, and they cast up the Summ: but in the buſineſs of their Souls, are barely led, and drawn aſide by the Opinions of other men? And this, even when they have an exact Scale</hi> (wherein to weigh all things) <hi>an exact Rule, or Square</hi> (whereby to meaſure them) <hi>the dictate of the Divine Laws. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech and intreat you all, that not minding what ſuch or ſuch a man ſaith about theſe things; you would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Holy Scriptures concerning them all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:64584:35"/>And if you conſider what kind of Auditors Chriſt had, you may ſoon come to a concluſion in this matter; and learn from thence what his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is.</p>
               <p>Were they not the promiſcuous multitude? People of all ſorts, and conditions? And will He take it ill to be read of thoſe, by whom He would be heard?</p>
               <p>Some will ſay, there is danger in reading; the words may be miſtaken, or perverted: And may they not be ſo in hearing? Can any Preacher, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, ſo frame his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that he can warrant not a word he ſaith ſhall be miſunderſtood, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreted, and turned to another ſenſe than he meant it?</p>
               <p>By this reaſon the poor people ſhall be taught nothing at all; if we muſt do them no good, becauſe ſome may poſſibly abuſe it, and turn it to their hurt.</p>
               <p>Nay, if God himſelf may not be heard by the people, ſpeaking to them in the vulgar Tongue; I ſee far leſs reaſon why men ſhould: who can ſay nothing but what may be wreſted and miſconſtrued.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:64584:36"/>Further yet; the wiſeſt and moſt learned may pervert and wreſt the Scriptures; and therefore if this be a reaſon, why they ſhould not be read, they muſt be wholly laid aſide, and none permitted to read them.</p>
               <p>The Scribes and Phariſees, I am ſure, did ſo; far more than the moſt ſimple people: And yet none will ſay, they ought not to have read the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, it being the profeſſion of the Scribes.</p>
               <p>None more obſtinately reſiſted Chriſt, than they who had theſe Holy Books perpetually in their hands; in which He was promiſed and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed. They were his moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Enemies, who were the allowed Expounders of the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: making uſe of all they read to oppoſe Him. And therefore either none, no not the moſt learned, no more than the ſimple, muſt read the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; for fear of doing themſelves and others harm by them: or this is not a good Reaſon againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peoples reading them; nor is it the reading them that doth hurt, but the reading them with a bad mind and with naughty affections.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:64584:36"/>The Learned may abuſe them, as well as the Unlearned, if they be ill diſpoſed: and the Unlearned may get good by them, as well as the Learned, if they be well affected.</p>
               <p>There are ſome things clearer, than that any can doubt of them, or ſtand in need of an Interpreter; the ſimpleſt may eaſily apprehend them, and be inſtructed by them, if they come with honeſt and good hearts to learn their Duty: and yet the wiſeſt will not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them, or not receive them, though never ſo plain, if their hearts be otherwiſe bent, and ill diſpoſed in their affections. They that have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted themſelves to this World, will be offended with them: even becauſe they are ſo plain, and directly croſs their intentions and deſigns.</p>
               <p>For what were the things, that made our Saviour ſo troubleſom to the Scribes and Phariſees? His Life was perfectly innocent; his Converſation free and friendly with all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; his Heart was open to give them an eaſie acceſs into his preſence and into his affections; his Power was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial; his Doctrine was moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64584:37"/>his Precepts juſt and good; his Promiſes exceeding great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious above all earthly Treaſure. The buſineſs therefore was, they were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of a Kingdom; in which they were honoured as the moſt Learned, adored as Saints, inriched with great Treaſures, eſteemed worthy of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: this they thought the happieſ: condition, this ſtate of things they wiſht might always be continued: but feared our Saviour would draw the hearts of the people from them, and that their Authority would be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by admitting his: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſet themſelves againſt him, and could not endure the light of his Goſpel; which ſhowed them how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle they muſt be content to be in this World, and only promiſed to make them great men in the Kingdom of Heaven; whereof they made no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>And it is to be feared, that for the very ſame reaſon ſome men in the Chriſtian World are againſt the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Scriptures, for which they were againſt the receiving of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt Himſelf. Their Authority,<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64584:37"/>they fear, will thereby be impaired: They ſhall not be able to lead the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whither they pleaſe, with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Belief: their eyes will be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſeeing how they have been abuſed, they will grow leſs credulous; and not ſo eaſily entertain thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which are very gainful to the Teachers, when they ſee they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unprofitable to them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them.</p>
               <p>I am ſure ſuch evil affections will never let men underſtand the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures aright: but incline the wiſeſt and moſt diſcerning men (if ſo ill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) to bend them, ſooner than any meaner perſons, to their own crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed intereſts.</p>
               <p>Thus I have finiſhed the firſt part of this Work; when I have made a few Reflections upon what hath been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed.</p>
               <p n="1">I. And <hi>Firſt</hi> of all this demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates how unreaſonable, unjuſt, and uncharitable (to ſay no worſe) the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church are: which deny to Chriſtian people that liberty, which God and his Church<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64584:38"/>have always allowed them. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition to read the Scriptures in the vulgar Tongue, is a manifeſt <hi>Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> There is an evident Change in the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, ſince St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s days, who beſtowed ſeveral Epiſtles upon divers Women, to preſs them to read them, and to teach them to their little Children. Which made <hi>Eſpencaeus,</hi> a Romiſh Biſhop, honeſtly ſay, that he could not but <hi>wonder, how that ſhould now be counted ſo peſtilent and capital, which the Ancients frequently commend as moſt wholeſom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> This Diſcourſe ſhould ſerve for a Caution to us, not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt our Souls with ſuch Guides, as err thus palpably, and I doubt wilfully, in ſo plain a buſineſs as this. For how eaſily will they miſtake, or miſlead their Followers, in other caſes? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where there may be ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, or ſome ſeeming Authority for it?</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And this ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline every one of us, to adhere moſt firmly and faithfully to this Church.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64584:38"/>Which is ſo <hi>ſincerely honeſt,</hi> that it fears not to be tryed by this Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, the Holy Scripture: ſo <hi>well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted,</hi> that Chriſtians cannot, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, deſire more free and plentiful means of their inſtruction, than they have, in all things neceſſary to their Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Which therefore let us take care we do not abuſe: and thereby help to confirm and harden the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in their Errours.</p>
               <p>We ought not, I have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to lay aſide the Holy Scriptures out of our hands (God forbid we ſhould conſent to that) but they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves require us, <hi>to lay aſide all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, that</hi> (coming thus with prepared minds)
<hi>with meekneſs we may receive the ingraft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed word, which is able to ſave our Souls,</hi> Jam. I. 21.</p>
               <p>That's the <hi>End</hi> for which we muſt read theſe Holy Books (as laying aſide all naughty affections is the <hi>Method</hi>) to know what we muſt do to be ſaved. Not to learn how to diſcourſe, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and argue, much leſs to cavil;<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64584:39"/>but how to live according to the Will of God in our ſeveral places: which is the way to everlaſting Salvation.</p>
               <p>And whatſoever belongs either to a godly life, or the neceſſary Articles of Chriſtian Faith, is ſo plainly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered there, that when we meet with any thing that is doubtful, or hard to be underſtood, we are told plainly enough what to do in that caſe. They themſelves direct us, not to <hi>be wiſe in our own conceits,</hi> not to <hi>lean to our own underſtanding;</hi> but to go and adviſe with thoſe whom God hath appointed to expound them to us. Who will either ſatisfie us what is the meaning of ſuch places; or that it is not of ſuch moment, that we need to trouble our ſelves about it.</p>
               <p>For theſe Books are ſo far from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us the leaſt incouragement to be bold and preſumptuous, to ſlight our Inſtructers, and much leſs, to deſpiſe our Governours, whether Civil or Spiritual; that there is Nothing they teach us more plainly, than to be humble and modeſt; and that as we ought to <hi>fear God,</hi> ſo likewiſe to <hi>honour the King</hi> and his Miniſters; and <hi>to obey<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64584:39"/>thoſe that watch over our Souls;</hi> nay, <hi>to eſteem them very highly in love for their work ſake.</hi> Which will diſpoſe us moſt certainly (if we be not carried away with pride, or any other vicious affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) to be ruled by them in dubious things: and, as it there follows in the Apoſtle, (1
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> V. 13.) <hi>to be at peace among our ſelves.</hi> I muſt beſeech there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Member of this Church, both for the honour of our Religion, and for the ſafety of their own Souls, to be as careful in this matter, as I would have them to be in reading the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Take your Guides along with you; do not think your ſelves ſafe, without their conduct; be not only willing, but deſirous to learn of them; reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence their Inſtructions; do not eaſily diſſent from them; be afraid to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them: eſpecially when you have reaſon to think them to be ſerious, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, knowing, and conſcientious men; who take care to inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves aright, that they may not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inform you.</p>
               <p>For ſuch men look upon themſelves to be bound (as hath been ſhown in<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64584:40"/>the Treatiſe of Tradition, <hi>pag.</hi> 24.) to guide themſelves in their Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, by <hi>what the Catholick Fathers and ancient Biſhops have taught out of the Doctrine of the Old and New Teſtament;</hi> and thereby preſerve their Flocks in the Truth of God's holy Word. And having a great regard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the ſenſe of that Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they live, which by their Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions they owne <hi>to have Authority in Controverſies of Faith,</hi> they will no leſs preſerve them in Unity and in Peace.</p>
               <p>To conclude; it is impoſſible but every body muſt reap great fruit by the reading of the Scriptures, if they read them for no other end; but that they may go away better from the reading of them, than they came to it: and that they may not accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date them to their own affections; but correct all their affections, and deſires, and the whole courſe of their life, by this exact Rule of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. According to which, if we ſquare our ſelves, we ſhall preſently learn; <hi>in difficult things to be wiſe unto ſobriety, and in plain things to be wiſe unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> that is, ſo wiſe as to do what<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64584:40"/>we certainly know to be our Duty; which is the only Wiſdom that the Scriptures magnifie. Which will be the ſureſt way, <hi>both to know more, and to know it better:</hi> that is, to feel the comfort of what we know, in a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and aſſured hope of everlaſting life; which God, who cannot lye, hath promiſed to us, in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:64584:41"/>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:64584:41"/>
            <head>PART II.</head>
            <p>HAving ſhewn in the foregoing Diſcourſe, that thoſe words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> (2. <hi>III.</hi> 16.) which are wont to be alledged againſt the reading of Holy Scriptures, do plainly ſuppoſe that the people did then read them: I proceed now in the next place to ſhew that the Apoſtle doth not deter men from reading them, by repreſenting the difficulties that are in them, and the danger of wreſting them. For he doth not affirm that <hi>all things</hi> are hard to be underſtood (and conſequently liable to be wreſted) but only that <hi>ſome things</hi> are of that nature:</p>
            <p>In treating of which, <hi>three</hi> things offer themſelves to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> that moſt things in the Holy Scriptures are ſo far from being hard to be underſtood, that they are eaſy: Nay, all things abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us, are very eaſy.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:64584:42"/>II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That thoſe things which are not ſo eaſy, may be underſtood; though there be ſome difficulty in it. That is, they will require ſome pains to underſtand them; which ſhould not deter us from read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but only make us laborious to find out the ſenſe of what we read.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When we do thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand, and heartily believe the things that are eaſie, it will abate much of that difficulty; and make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things more eaſie.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>I begin with the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe; the Apoſtle only ſaith, <hi>ſome things</hi> are hard to be underſtood; which ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that moſt are not; but rather ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: as all thoſe things, eſpecially, are, which are abſolutely neceſſary to be known, and believed, and done, for the obtaining Salvation.</p>
               <p>That which makes things eaſie to be underſtood, is the plain and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous delivery of them, in the words wherein they are written, or ſpoken.<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64584:42"/>Now nothing an be plainer, or clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, than the words, wherein all the great Chriſtian Truths are revealed and delivered to us: which are ſo far from being obſcure, that it is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to ſee the light, than it is to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and underſtand the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
               <p>I will inſtance in ſome particulars; and have an Eye all the way upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles (to which S. <hi>Peter</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly thought to have reſpect) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, though ſome things be difficult, yet theſe are moſt clearly diſcovered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That there is but <hi>one God, the Father, of whom are all things,</hi> as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly writes, 1 Cor. <hi>VIII</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That He alone is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped (as our Bleſſed Saviour remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers us out of <hi>Moſes, IV.</hi> Matt. 10.) was the great thing preſſed in his very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into any place where he preach'd, 1 Theſſ. <hi>l.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>XVII.</hi> Acts 23, 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As our Lord teaches us, that we are ingaged by our Baptiſm, to worſhip one God, in three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, XXVIII.
<hi>Matth.</hi> 19. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms the ſame plainly enough, in that Solemn Prayer for the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:64584:43"/>2. XIII. ult. <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Love of God, and the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt, be with you all.</hi> Eſpecially if it be compared with thoſe places, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he affirms our Saviour, <hi>to be over all, God bleſſed for ever,</hi> IX. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. and the Spirit, to
<hi>ſearch even the deep things of God;</hi> that is, to know his Mind exactly: for ſo it follows (1 <hi>Cor. II.</hi> 10, 11.) that as <hi>none can know the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of man, which is in him: ſo the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.</hi> Which plainly tells us, if we mind it, that the Spirit of God is <hi>in God,</hi> as the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of man is <hi>in man:</hi> that is, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is God himſelf, and therefore fully acquainted with him in all things.</p>
               <p>There is ſome little labour indeed, in making this deduction; but it is very eaſie, if we conſider all theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> And the Nature of God, none can poſſibly be ignorant of, who doth but look into the Holy Books. Where he will immediately ſee Him repreſented to be Almighty, moſt Wiſe, moſt Gracious, Faithful to his<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64584:43"/>Word, and the living God, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever. Which are Truths written there, in ſuch great Letters, that every one who runs (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaks) and doth but caſt a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient eye upon them, may eaſily read them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Particularly, his infinite love and kindneſs towards us the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, lies before us ſo fairly, and ſhines ſo brightly in our eyes; that if we do not wilfully ſhut them, we cannot but read it to our infinite ſatisfaction. <hi>For ſo God loved the world,</hi> ſaith our Lord Himſelf, <hi>that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life. For God ſent not his Son into the world, to condemn the world; but that the world through him might be ſaved,</hi> III. John 16, 17. And ſo St.
<hi>Paul</hi> writes, <hi>But God who is rich in mercy, for his great love wherewith he loved us, even when we were dead in ſins, hath quickened us together with Chriſt Jeſus (by Grace ye are ſaved) And hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together, in heavenly places, in Chriſt Jeſus. That in the ages to come<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64584:44"/>he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his Grace, in his kindneſs towards us through Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> II. Epheſ. 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>Who can doubt at all of the favour of God, his exceeding great and rich favour towards us, who doth but caſt his eyes on ſuch words as theſe; and believes the Truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt? Which were written for this very end, that in all future Ages of the World, after the Apoſtles were gone, men might diſcern how abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant the Grace of God is, in his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs manifeſted towards us in our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord. And therefore we, in this Age of the World, as well as all that were before us, may conclude without any ſcruple, that <hi>God is Love</hi> (as St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks) and that he will be good to us, for Chriſt's ſake, though we have greatly offended his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> For that is the next thing; the kindneſs of God towards ſinful men, and his readineſs to pardon them and receive them into his favour and love again, is here alſo ſo perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly revealed, that there need be no queſtion made of it. <hi>In this was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted the love of God towards us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64584:44"/>that God ſent his only begotten Son into the world, that we might live through him. Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his Son to be the propitiation for our ſins,</hi> 1 John IV. 9, 10.</p>
               <p>And in the ſame manner writes St. <hi>Paul, After the kindneſs and love,</hi> or pity, <hi>of God our Saviour towards man appeared, not by works of righteouſneſs that we have done, but according to his mercy he ſaved us, by the waſhing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and the renewing of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. That being juſtified by his Grace, we ſhould be made heirs, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the hope of Eternal life,</hi> III. Tit. 4, 5.</p>
               <p>Nay, for this very end, he ſaith, God ſhewed mercy to him, though a very great Sinner, a Blaſphemer of Chriſt, a Perſecutor of his Diſciples, that men might be incouraged to hope in God; if they would repent and turn to Him, as he did, 1 <hi>Tim. I.</hi> 14, 15, 16, &amp;c. Read the place, and you will ſee, that all the wit of man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deviſe plainer and clearer words, to expreſs the exceeding Grace of God towards all men: which is declared<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64584:45"/>ſo fully, as well as familiarly, that his words need no Commentary to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain them, and make them more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be underſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> With the ſame Evidence, the Goſpel ſpeaks of the way and means, whereby this Forgiveneſs was procured for us: and that is by the Death, and by the Reſurrection of our Lord Jeſus.
<hi>Who was delivered,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>for our offences, and roſe again for our juſtification,</hi> IV. Rom. ult. <hi>In whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveneſs of ſins, according to the riches of his Grace,</hi> I. Epheſ. 7. <hi>It is God that juſtifies, who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again; who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for us; who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt?</hi> &amp;c. VIII.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 34, 35, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It would be endleſs to recite all that the Scriptures ſpeak on this ſubject; in terms as plain and clear as theſe: So that we cannot reaſonably doubt, if we believe theſe Books, <hi>that by one offering of Himſelf, he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified,</hi> as the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:64584:45"/>Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſpeaks, X. 12, 13, 14.
<hi>This man after he had offered one Sacrifice for ſins, for ever ſate down at the right hand of God; from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth expecting, till his enemies be made his footſtool: For by one offering he hath perfected for ever,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They that would make any other Satisfaction neceſſary, by the Merits of Saints; or any other Oblation of Chriſt neceſſary, but that one which he Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf offered, directly contradict the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words of this Book; which are as eaſie to be underſtood, as any that the moſt ſtudied invention of men can indite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> And ſo is the way and means, whereby theſe Bleſſings, thus purchaſed, are communicated to us, <hi>viz.</hi> the Mediation and Interceſſion of Chriſt Jeſus, on our behalf, whereby
<hi>he can ſave us to the utmoſt, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for us,</hi> VII. <hi>Heb.</hi> 25. Nor is there any other that can perform this Office for us, but he; for as <hi>there is one God, ſo one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as St.
<hi>Paul</hi> teaches in ſo many words, 1 <hi>Tim. II.</hi> 4. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64584:46"/>we cannot but in reaſon think, he means there is <hi>no more than One Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> as, it is certain, there is <hi>no more than one God:</hi> who communicates his Mind to us by this alone Mediator, as we muſt addreſs our ſelves to Him by no other.</p>
               <p>Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares more fully in 1 <hi>Cor. VIII.</hi> 5, 6. Where he ſaith, though there be <hi>many that are called Gods (as there are gods many, and lords many) yet to us</hi> (Chriſtians)
<hi>there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things, and we in</hi> (or
<hi>for,</hi> or <hi>to</hi>) <hi>him; and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things, and we by him.</hi> That is, As there is but one ſole Fountain of all good, unto whom we are to direct our Prayers, and all we do (for the firſt Cauſe muſt be our laſt End) ſo He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives all unto us by his Son Jeſus Chriſt alone; by whom therefore, and by Him alone, we are to go to God the Father, for what we are deſirous to receive from Him. None elſe in Heaven or Earth, is capable of this Honour, but this great Lord alone (whom <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loveth, and hath given all things into his hands</hi> (III. <hi>John</hi> 35.) as any<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64584:46"/>one that reads this place ſeriouſly, may eaſily diſcern.</p>
               <p>And therefore they who betake themſelves unto any other Patron, to recommend them to the Heavenly Grace, are concerned to hide this Book from the Peoples Eyes; and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them from reading it, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, it is obſcure and hard to be underſtood. For they who do read it, ſee this truth ſo fully and expreſly aſſerted there, that, if their minds be not prejudiced, they cannot think it ſafe to implore the aſſiſtance of any other in the Heavenly Court: which apparently derogates from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Lord, and is highly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, upon many accounts, to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God. Who hath appointed Him to take care of our affairs, who loves us better than any Saint or Angel can do, becauſe he dyed for us; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is more inclined to have compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon us, becauſe he hath that feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our infirmities, which no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel was ever touched withal, nor any Saint in ſuch a degree as he was: Who can alſo do more for us, than all the Angels in Heaven put together; being the Lord of Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:64584:47"/>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Which is another thing here clearly revealed; the Power and Glory of the Lord Jeſus, at the right Hand of God. <hi>We all with open face</hi> (without any Veil drawn before our Eyes) <hi>behold as in a Glaſs the Glory of the Lord,</hi> as St.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 2 Cor. <hi>III.</hi> ult. The Goſpel, that is, which he preached, and which we read, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents his tranſcendent Majeſty ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently; that our own Face doth not appear more clearly to us in a Glaſs, than Chriſt is ſet before us there, as advanced <hi>far above all Principality and Power</hi> (to uſe his words in another place, <hi>I.</hi> Epheſ. 21.) <hi>and Might and Dominion, and every name that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not only in this World, but alſo in that which is to come.</hi> God having
<hi>put all things under his Feet, and given him to be Head over all things to the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What may we not expect from ſo great a Prince, who hath all things at his command; and that for the good of his Church: if we faithfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs our ſelves to God by Him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly,</hi> I might ſay the like of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64584:47"/>reſt of the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith; which are here plainly taught. But I ſhall only add that, as the way and means whereby Chriſt procured and doth diſpenſe the Divine Grace to us, is evidently declared in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures: ſo is the means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may hope to obtain the Benefit of his Sacrifice, Satisfaction and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion with God for us. <hi>Repent, and be converted, and your ſins ſhall be blotted out.</hi> (III. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.) are words plain enough to be underſtood. And ſo are theſe, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will refreſh you. Take my Yoke upon you, and learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye ſhall find reſt unto your Souls.</hi> XI.
<hi>Matth.</hi> 28, 29. And theſe; <hi>In Chriſt Jeſus, neither Circumciſion avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but Faith working by Love; a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; or keeping the Commandments of God.</hi> For in all theſe terms, for the greater clearneſs ſake, and that no man may be miſtaken, is this matter declared by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> VII.
19. V. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. VI. <hi>Gal.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>And therefore that <hi>the Grace of the<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64584:48"/>Goſpel teaches us, that, denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Worldly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World</hi> (2 <hi>Tit.</hi> II. 12.) is as clear as the Sun.</p>
               <p>Nor are the particular duties, which belong to every ones place and ſtate, leſs clear and conſpicuous, than theſe general lines of our Duty, which the Apoſtle hath drawn in thoſe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive words. For when the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> directs his Speech (as he doth commonly in the latter part of his Epiſtles) unto Maſters of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Servants, unto Husbands and Wives, Fathers and Children; his Rules are as plain and eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by us now, as they were to thoſe perſons who firſt received them.</p>
               <p>So plain and eaſie they are unto all Ages, ſo familiar, eſpecially to men of meaner rank, that <hi>I much doubt</hi> (ſaith a great Champion of our Church, in his Comments on the Creed<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Lib. 2. Cap. 12.</note>) <hi>whether the Pope himſelf, and the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave of Cardinals, would be able in this preſent Age, to ſpeak ſo plainly unto the capacity, or ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64584:48"/>to the experience of men of their Quality unto whom the Apoſtle wrote. For, ſetting aſide the abſolute Truth and Infallibility of his Doctrines, the manner of delivering them is ſo familiar, ſo low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo heartily humble, ſo natural, and ſo well-befitting ſuch mens diſpoſition in their ſober thoughts, as were impoſſible for the Pope to attain unto, or imitate; unleſs he would lay aſide his Court-State, and for ſeven years addict himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to familiarity, with ſuch men in a Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame may be ſaid concerning his way of ſpeaking, when he ſets down any other Chriſtian Duties, whether private or publick. No man could ever pretend any difficulty in this part of the Holy Writings, which treat of a Holy Life. All the difficulty is in mens wills; to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to conſent to be governed by theſe Laws, which they cannot chuſe but well enough underſtand.</p>
               <p>And that they may be perſwaded, Chriſt hath left us exceeding great and precious Promiſes, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the greateſt part of the Goſpel-Grace: the very end of which is to<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64584:49"/>move us to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly. <hi>Having therefore theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, (dearly beloved) let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. VII. 1.</p>
               <p>What words can be more perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than theſe? And with the ſame clearneſs theſe Books pronounce the indiſpenſable neceſſity of a holy life; without which the riches of God's Grace cannot ſave us.
<hi>Follow peace and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> XII. Heb. 14. <hi>Know ye not, that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? Be not deceived, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers,</hi> &amp;c <hi>nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. VI. 9, 10. <hi>Now the works of the fleſh are manifeſt</hi> (mark that word) <hi>adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, fornication, uncleanneſs, laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, emulation, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, murders, drunkenneſs, revellings, and ſuch like; of which I have told you before in times paſt, that they which do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64584:49"/>Kingdom of God. But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance; againſt ſuch there is no law. And they that are Chriſt's have crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts. If we live in the Spirit, let us alſo walk in the Spirit,</hi> V. Gal. 19, 20, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay more? All the Promiſes of God, which put us in <hi>hope;</hi> and all his Threatnings, which are deſigned to put us in
<hi>fear</hi> (upon which two Hinges, all Religion turns) are, you ſee already, declared ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and clearly, that there can be no diſpute about them. For <hi>this is the promiſe, which he hath promiſed, even Eternal life,</hi> 1 Joh. II. 25. and <hi>the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven against all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men, who hold the truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> I. Rom. 18. For <hi>He will render to every man according to his deeds; to them who by patient continuance in well doing ſeek for honour, glory and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, eternal life: But to them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs, indignation and wrath; tribulation and anguiſh upon<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64584:50"/>every ſoul of man that doth evil, of the Jew firſt, and alſo of the Gentile. But glory, honour and peace to every man that worketh good, to the Jew firſt, and alſo to the Gentile. For there is no reſpect of perſons with God,</hi> II. Rom. 6, 7, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If theſe words be not intelligible, there can be no ſuch thing as plain ſpeaking in the World? And it is as plainly and intelligibly written, that <hi>God hath appointed a day wherein he will judge the world in righteouſneſs,</hi> (XVII. <hi>Acts</hi> 31.) when he will make good all his Promiſes and Threatnings; and that our Lord Chriſt is that great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by whom He will judge it. All our labour, all our Art, can never make a Propoſition to be underſtood, if all theſe things which I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned (which are the ſubſtance of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) be not obvious and clear to all, who will take the pains to read the Holy Scriptures, and conſider them.</p>
               <p>And therefore they do a great inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Grace of God, and to the Care and Love of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Head of the Church; who endeavour to perſwade us, the Holy Scriptures are ſo obſcure, that it is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64584:50"/>not fit the people ſhould look into them, for fear of miſtaking, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelves into dangerous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Hereſies. They may do ſo, though they do not read the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, by following their own vain imaginations, and by dreaming upon that which they hear out of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or which ſtarts up in their own fancy: but if they look into the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to know how to be ſaved, and have no other end, nor neglect hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to implore the Divine guidance, they cannot miſtake; but may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully ſatisfied. For God hath told usall, that <hi>Jeſus is the Saviour;</hi> and that he is the Author of Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>to them that obey Him;</hi> and his <hi>Commandments,</hi> wherein we are to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Him, as they are not <hi>grievous,</hi> ſo they are <hi>obvious,</hi> and may be met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all every where, if we have a mind to learn them; and he hath ſet
<hi>Paſtors and Teachers</hi> in his Church, <hi>for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt: till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c. IV. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:64584:51"/>11, 12, 13. So that no man, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch directors, can miſs the way that leads to Eternal life; unleſs both he and they will wilfully ſhut their eyes: and on purpoſe turn aſide from the path, which the Holy Scripture ſhows unto them. And if the words of the Spirit of God (which are as bright as a Lamp, to give light unto our feet) may be miſtaken or abuſed; then no man, no company of men; no Interpreter, no Council, can draw up any words but they may be perverted, by thoſe who have no mind to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by them; but are concerned to put another ſenſe, than they intended, upon them.</p>
               <p>And indeed it is no ſlight Argument that the Holy Scriptures are eaſie to be underſtood in all things neceſſary for our Inſtruction, becauſe God would have all, even the meaneſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, to read them: as I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the foregoing Part of this work, beyond any reaſonable contradiction. It would have been in vain to require men, <hi>to ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> as not only God, but his Church in ancient times, did; if they could not readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64584:51"/>there meet with ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>The Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I know, argue the quite contrary way; therefore you ſhould not read them, becauſe they are obſcure. But which will you chuſe to believe? God, who bids you read them, from whence you may conclude they are not obſcure; or men, who bid you not read them, becauſe they are obſcure? You may moſt ſafely conclude they are not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, becauſe God bids you read them; for this is a right Concluſion from Divine Premiſſes: whereas the other Concluſion that you ſhould not read them, is drawn from a falſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, directly contradictory to what follows from the Command of God to be converſant in them; which is, that they are not ſo obſcure, but in things neceſſary we may eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. Otherwiſe, our Bleſſed Lord, the Wiſdom of the Father, would not have bidden men ſearch them: nor would his Apoſtles have ceaſed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their pains, till they had made ſuch things plainer, if they had not thought they had ſet them down ſo plainly in their Writings, that no man,<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64584:52"/>who would read, could be ignorant of them.</p>
               <p>That's another thing worthy obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; That the very End for which the Goſpel was written by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, reproves this Pretence of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, it was that we might believe, XX.
<hi>Joh. ult. Theſe things are written, that ye might believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God; and that believing, ye might have life through his Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By whoſe Authority did St. <hi>John</hi> write; or by whoſe aſſiſtance did he perform this work? Was it not by our Saviour's, and by the guidance of the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <p>And to what purpoſe was he inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but to work Faith in thoſe mens Souls, who read his Writings? And what Faith was this? only the belief of ſome few things, which are clear enough, but not ſufficient to make us wiſe unto Salvation. No ſuch matter. He wrote that we might have ſo much Faith, as ſhould give us Eternal life, through Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Now who can believe, that he who wrote by that Spirit, which perfectly<pb n="95" facs="tcp:64584:52"/>knew the ſeveral Tempers and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of every Age; and with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to breed ſaving Faith in their Souls, ſhould yet write ſo obſcurely, that he could not be underſtood of them, for whoſe good and benefit he wrote?</p>
               <p>Nothing but intereſt; that is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that very wicked Temper, which blinded the Jews, and made them deny our Saviour and crucifie him, can induce a man to be of this opinion.</p>
               <p>It will be replyed, I know by ſome, that however, here is a confeſſion, that <hi>ſome things</hi> are hard to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: and therefore it is beſt to keep the Scriptures from the people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may do themſelves hurt by thoſe things.</p>
               <p>Unto which I have anſwered alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; that if they ſeek for Nothing but Salvation, and how to pleaſe God in order thereunto; they will not do themſelves hurt by any thing they meet withal in the Holy Writings. But for further ſatisfaction, I ſhall proceed to give a brief account of the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing, I propounded to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: which is,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:64584:53"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>THAT the Apoſtle doth not ſay ſome things <hi>cannot</hi> be underſtood; but that they are <hi>hard</hi> to be underſtood. There is ſome labour required to the underſtanding them: which, if we will take, we may comprehend their meaning.</p>
               <p>It would be a long Work to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what things, in St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> may be thought to point at, as difficult to be underſtood. But the inquiry might be very much ſhortned, by one ſmall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: which may be ſufficient to inform us, That, if men take heed, the Scriptures are not ſo difficult to be underſtood; as Lazineſs, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Reading, and Intereſt would make them.</p>
               <p>It is only this; to what the word <hi>WHICH</hi> relates, when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>In WHICH are ſome things,</hi> &amp;c. Whether to St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, or to thoſe things, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> is treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of in this Chapter, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth in ſome of his Epiſtles? And it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64584:53"/>to thoſe, who will be at ſo much pains, as to ask any honeſt man that underſtands the Original Language; that it refers, not to all St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but to thoſe things of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had been diſcourſing. For the words are not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in which Epiſtles,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in which things,</hi> or <hi>among which</hi> things, ſome are hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood</p>
               <p>Now that which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had been ſpeaking of, is the
<hi>Coming of our Lord;</hi> concerning which he ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo had written: and therefore it is moſt reaſonable to determine that S. <hi>Peter</hi> here means, that in thoſe things, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had written in his Epiſtles, about <hi>Chriſt's Coming,</hi> there were ſome things not ſo eaſie to be underſtood as the reſt.</p>
               <p>And what great matter is it, if we be ignorant of <hi>ſome things</hi> relating to his Coming; ſince we know and are certain, by undoubted words of the Apoſtles, that He will come; and come to render unto all according to their works?</p>
               <p>Let us believe this, and then we ſhall find no difficulty in the uſe which<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64584:54"/>St. <hi>Peter</hi> makes of it, in the
<hi>eleventh</hi> verſe. <hi>What manner of perſons ought we to be in all holy converſation and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be very ill for us, if Chriſt ſhould come now, and find us, inſtead of reforming our lives, by practiſing the plain Truths of the Goſpel, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting againſt that Goſpel, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reflections upon it; as an obſcure Book, which is more apt to breed Hereſies, than to teach men the way to Heaven. And whenſoever He doth come, it will not be eaſie for ſome men to anſwer this Charge, which will be brought againſt them, of aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Will and Teſtament on this faſhion; as if it were apt to make his Children fall out, and not rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together in pious Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>But let thoſe who are concern'd look to that; let us, who enjoy the liberty of reading his Holy Will, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged ſo to do, only endeavour, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>to have our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation as becomes the Goſpel.</hi> And when we meet with any thing which we do not underſtand therein; let our next<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64584:54"/>thought be, that there is enough which we do underſtand: and that if we pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it, and will take pains, we may in time underſtand the reſt, as far as concerns us in our ſtate and condition of life.</p>
               <p>For it is eaſie to ſhow, that if we extend the meaning of St. <hi>Peter</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as we are wont to do) and look into all thoſe parts of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that are thought the hardeſt to be underſtood; we may, with ſome diligence and obſervation, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the meaning of them well enough. And till we uſe that diligence, we ought not to accuſe the Scriptures of obſcurity, but our ſelves of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>All, it is true, cannot uſe that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence which is neceſſary to underſtand him in all points; becauſe their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will not permit it: but it is as true, that, as it is not neceſſary they ſhould underſtand him in all things ſo, if they could uſe that diligence which is requiſite, they might (for any thing that can be ſeen in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s words) underſtand him thoroughout. For he only ſaith, there are difficult things<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64584:55"/>in St. <hi>Paul:</hi> but difficulties are ſhort of impoſſibilities; and we ſee very great difficulties, in other matters, overcome by mens induſtry and God's bleſſing. And therefore they may be overcome here, by thoſe who make it their buſineſs, and have capacity to comprehend his meaning.</p>
               <p>And if they do not underſtand every particular expreſſion or paſſage; yet his ſcope and drift, in the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, may with careful attention and obſervation, be clearly diſcerned.</p>
               <p>At leaſt, there is Nothing in St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s words which contradict this; and therefore they are vainly alledged to prove the obſcurity and difficulty of the Scriptures: when they can extend but to
<hi>ſome places</hi> of Scripture, <hi>i. e.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles; and but to <hi>ſome things</hi> in them; nay, but to ſome things, I have ſhown, in <hi>one particular</hi> Diſcourſe in them, about the Coming of Chriſt; which have no further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity in them neither, but what is only an exerciſe of our diligence, by which they may be underſtood.</p>
               <p>But juſt thus other places are wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prove the obſcurity of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.<pb n="101" facs="tcp:64584:55"/>I will inſtance in one or two. The Abridger of Controverſies fears not to alledge the VIII.
<hi>Acts</hi> 30, 31. to this purpoſe. Where St. <hi>Philip</hi> asks the Eunuch, if he underſtood what he read, and he confeſſes he did not; but asks him again, <hi>How can I, except ſome man ſhould guide me?</hi> From whence he concludes, they are not eaſie to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
               <p>To which the Reply is ſo eaſie, that he muſt have a film before his eyes, who doth not ſee that this place is an Argument againſt them that alledge it. For it proves (as I ſhowed in the firſt Part) that men did then read the Scriptures, though they did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what they read. And it proves not that the Eunuch underſtood No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but only that he did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that particular place which St. <hi>Philip</hi> found him reading. And that was a place in a Prophecy, which hath ſome obſcurity in it, till it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, though not afterward. And it was but one thing he did not underſtand in that Prophecy: for he knew <hi>what</hi> the Prophet ſaid, but could not tell of <hi>whom. I pray thee tell me,</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:64584:56"/>ſaith he to the Evangeliſt, <hi>of whom speaketh the Prophet, of himſelf, or of ſome other?</hi> That was all the inquiry? the difficulty lying in that one ſingle point, and in that alſo only for a time: for by the help of an Interpreter he ſoon underſtood the Prophecy was fulfilled, and in whom it was fulfilled. So that this very place hath now no difficulty at all in it unto us, when we read it; though it was at that time difficult to him.</p>
               <p>What a number of inſufficiencies are there in this allegation (as Biſhop <hi>Montague</hi> juſtly complains) to prove the Scriptures are hard to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood? All that can be made of it is, that one place of Scripture was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure; in a particular caſe; and in one point only of that caſe; and at that time; and (I may further add) to a ſtranger, who was not of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Nation; and ſo was not from the beginning acquainted with their Books: who notwithſtanding, with a little help, preſently found it was no longer hard to be underſtood; but very eaſie, as it is now to us.</p>
               <p>This is enough both to ſhow how<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64584:56"/>inſufficient the proofs are which are brought to oppoſe our Doctrine; and that the difficulties we at preſent find in ſome places, may be overcome; and that one means to overcome them, is by the help of a wiſe Interpreter: who may (in many caſes at leaſt) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſatisfie us, and take away the obſcurity.</p>
               <p>There is another inſtance of ſuch weak proofs, in the ſame Author: who alledges XXIV. <hi>Luke</hi> 25. to prove the difficulty of underſtanding the Scriptures, and therefore the danger of reading them; becauſe the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt themſelves, who had been taught by him, did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, and therefore are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached by our Saviour in theſe ſharp terms, <hi>O fools and ſlow of heart to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all the Prophets have ſpoken,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Where it is manifeſt, they were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome parts of Scripture which they did not underſtand; and thoſe were the
<hi>Prophets,</hi> which had ſome obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as I ſaid, till their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and Prophecies only concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> his Death and Paſſion which he was to undergo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64584:57"/>he could aſcend to the Throne of his Glory: which were hard to them at that preſent, but are now eaſie by our Saviour's interpretation: and the queſtion is not, what the Scriptures were in <hi>thoſe days</hi> (when notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they read them, or elſe they could not have been blamed for not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding them) but what they are <hi>now</hi> unto us, who have the Writings of the Apoſtles whom He illuminated: And <hi>laſtly,</hi> his calling them <hi>Fools,</hi> for their ſlowneſs and dulneſs to believe, is an evident proof that even <hi>then,</hi> there was not ſo much a diſability in the two Diſciples, to underſtand what the Prophets ſaid; as a non-attention of mind, heedleſneſs, and want of conſideration, to things which were not of themſelves obſcure and difficult.</p>
               <p>However, our Lord had pity upon them all, and <hi>opened their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they might underſtand the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> v. 45. which the pooreſt Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church do now, in thoſe things wherein they were at that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ignorant; being fully perſwaded, <hi>that it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe from the dead the third day,</hi> which<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64584:57"/>were the things he then ſhowed them, were written of him.</p>
               <p>I conclude this with a brief ſtate of this Caſe. Some places of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture are hard to be underſtood by ſome perſons, and by ſome capacities, and in ſome ages and times, and ſome matters, that are not of general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment: but in that which concerns men of all ages, capacities and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and to every man in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and vocation, according to the meaſure of God's gifts beſtowed on him, we affirm, with the greateſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the Scripture is plain and eaſie to be underſtood: provided men have a will to learn what they are to believe and do, though it be never ſo croſs to their inclinations, intereſts, affections and paſſions. If theſe be ſuffered to intermeddle, the Goſpel tells us before-hand, in plain words, that men will not ſee, even when they ſee: according to thoſe words very often mentioned by our Lord and by his Apoſtles, <hi>Hearing ye ſhall hear, and ſhall not underſtand; and ſeeing ye ſhall ſee, and ſhall not perceive,</hi> &amp;c. by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that is, of their pride and ſelf-conceit,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64584:58"/>worldly-mindedneſs and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and ſuch like things: which blinded the eyes of thoſe, that <hi>loved darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds were evil.</hi> But <hi>this was their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> (as our Saviour tells us in the ſame breath, III.
<hi>John</hi> 19.) which it could not have been, unleſs the Mind and Will of God had been clearly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>WHICH leads me now to the <hi>third</hi> thing propoſed to Conſideration, in this <hi>Part</hi> of my Diſcourſe; that when we have thoroughly digeſted, and do heartily believe the things, that are eaſie and plain, in the Holy Scripture, that will abate much of the difficulty which is in other places; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our minds for acquaintance with them. Which I might wave here in this place, becauſe it will be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently cleared in the <hi>laſt Part</hi> of this little Treatiſe; concerning thoſe that
<hi>wreſt</hi> the Scriptures to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>But ſince it is profitable to have<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64584:58"/>things diſtinctly repreſented; I ſhall ſay ſomething to it by it ſelf.</p>
               <p>There is a near Alliance between all Truths: and the more familiar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are to our minds, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſed we are to come to the knowledge of all the reſt. But there are ſome of greater force than others, to widen the capacity of our minds, for the entertainment of Divine Truth; and to free them from all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite qualities and impediments, that they may entertain it eaſily. And they are a deep ſenſe of, and an hearty affection unto, all thoſe plain Leſſons, which teach us our whole Chriſtian duty: which if we thoroughly learn, we are certainly the Friends of God; and the more likely to be illuminated by him to underſtand the higheſt My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, as far as we are concerned in them, and our minds are able to reach them. For <hi>the ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him: and his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is to make them know it,</hi> XXV. Pſal. 14.</p>
               <p>And therefore it was no ill advice, which Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi> (if I miſtake not) gave for the reading of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64584:59"/>
                  <hi>to begin always at the latter end of them.</hi> For were we well verſed therein; by a ſerious ſtudy, that is, and ſincere practice of thoſe Chriſtian duties, which he there commends un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, we ſhould ſee the way more clearly, to come to the ſenſe of the former part of them: which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly harder to be underſtood than the latter.</p>
               <p>For our minds being truly humble and heavenly, and thereby ſedate and quiet, free from ambition, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or any ſecular deſire and deſign, they would be more ſerene and clear in themſelves; and alſo ſitter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive irradiations from above. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we might certainly diſcern, thus much (which is the main thing we are concerned to know) what the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral aim and ſcope of the Apoſtle is in the former part of his Epiſtles; though we did not underſtand the meaning and coherence of every particular Verſe.</p>
               <p>In that, it muſt be confeſſed, there is ſometimes no ſmall difficulty; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the Apoſtle writing againſt the Diſputers of that Age, we cannot, at<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64584:59"/>this diſtance, certainly know every little conceit or ſubtilty of theirs, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he briefly reflects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes, as he paſſes along. And yet notwithſtanding, we may be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied in the main Points of Doctrine, which he either aſſerts or oppoſes: which is the only thing of uſe to us; and enough to reward the painful inquiries of the moſt Learned men among us. Who by all their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies cannot, perhaps, attain to the knowledge of every particular paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; nay, will not ſee thoſe things that are moſt conſpicuous to others, if they do not amend their lives by the clear light of the Scripture in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places.</p>
               <p>For of this we may be certain, that <hi>it is the good pleaſure of God</hi> (as an excellent Man ſpeaks) <hi>and his unalter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Decree, that the Holy Scriptures</hi> (at leaſt in their drift and deſign)
<hi>ſhall be plain and eaſie to ſuch, as faithfully pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, their moſt plain and eaſie Precepts: but hard and difficult to be underſtood aright, of ſuch as wilfully tranſgreſs them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is nothing more perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64584:60"/>ſet down in Holy Scripture, than this; as would be eaſie to ſhow (if it would not inlarge this Book too much) from ſuch words as thoſe of St. <hi>Peter, God reſiſteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble.</hi> And therefore ſhould we admit of any Authority equivalent to the Holy Scriptures, the queſtion would ſtill remain, Whether the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſallibility of that Authority could take away that blindneſs of heart, which by God's juſt Judgment, falls upon all thoſe, who <hi>detain the Truth of God in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> If for their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to evident and plain Truths. God puniſh them with ſuch ſpiritual darkneſs, that they diſcern not his Will revealed in his written Word, no other infallible Authority can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten them; and make thoſe ſcales fall from their eyes, which hinder their ſight in the means of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They will everlaſtingly go on in darkneſs; becauſe having Light preſented to them, they preferred darkneſs before it. Thoſe naughty affections, which have kept the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, from ſhining into them, will cloſe their<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64584:60"/>eyes ſo faſt, that no other Light will open them. But they muſt either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and follow the plain directions of Holy Scripture, and recover their ſight by a ſincere practice of known Duties; or walk on ſtill in darkneſs, and remain in the ſhadow of death to the end of their days.</p>
               <p>Unto which plain direction, if men would unfeignedly ſubmit; if thereby they were not led to the underſtanding of harder Scriptures, they would how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever have this benefit; that they would be ſecured from miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. My meaning is, that by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, believing, and keeping cloſe, to the practice as well as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of the eaſie and evident Truths of the Goſpel, we ſhould be preſerved from putting any dangerous interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon thoſe places which are hard and difficult. Ignorant of them we might continue, or perhaps mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake their meaning: but ſtill inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently; ſo as not to do hurt to our ſelves or others by them.</p>
               <p>An illuſtrious Example of which we have in St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Book <hi>De Fide &amp; Operibus.</hi> Where diſcourſing
<hi>(Chap.<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64584:61"/>XV.)</hi> upon that place of St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> III. 12, 13. (which he takes to be one of thoſe, which St.
<hi>Peter</hi> ſaith are hard to be underſtood in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles) he tells us that ſome underſtood, <hi>the building gold, ſilver, precious ſtones upon this foundation,</hi> to be meant of adding good works to Faith in Chriſt: and building <hi>Wood, hay, ſtubble</hi> upon it, to be meant of thoſe that held the ſame Faith, but did evil. From whence they fanſied, that by certain pains of Fire, ſuch evil men might be purged, to obtain Salvation, by virtue of the Foundation; that is, by a right Faith only: becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>v.</hi> 15. they <hi>ſhould be ſaved, yet ſo as by fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if this be a true interpretation of this place, ſaith that Excellent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then all thoſe places of Scripture, which have no obſcurity, no ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity in them, muſt be taken to be falſe. As for Example, that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>Though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have no Charity, I am Nothing:</hi> and that of St. <hi>James, What doth it profit, brethren, if a man ſay he hath faith, but hath no works? Can<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64584:61"/>faith ſave him?</hi> And that place alſo will be ſalſe, <hi>Be not deceived, neither fornicators, nor they that ſerve Idols, nor Adulterers,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> And that alſo, <hi>The Works of the ſleſh are manifeſt, which are, adultery, fornication, uncleanneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of which I tell you again, as I have done formerly, that they who do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Theſe are all falſe, if that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation be true. St.
<hi>Paul</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts himſelf; and in this obſcure place, claſhes with his plain words: for according to this Expoſition, if men only believe and be baptized, they ſhall be ſaved by fire, though they perſevere in ſuch wicked courſes as thoſe now mentioned.</p>
               <p>And then I do not ſee to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our Lord ſaid,
<hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keep the Commandments;</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him what belongs unto good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And how will that be true, which he tells us he will ſay to them on his left hand, <hi>Go ye curſed,</hi> &amp;c. whom He ſends to Hell-fire, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not believe on him, but becauſe they did not do good works.<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64584:62"/>Thus that Father goes on, heaping up a great many other places, which evidently ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe, and then concludes:
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">If therefore theſe things, and innumerable others, which may be found in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures without any ambiguity, be falſe; then that ſenſe may be true concerning the <hi>wood, hay and ſtubble, viz.</hi> that they ſhall be ſaved by ſire, who only holding Faith in Chriſt, have neglected good Works. <hi>Si au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; vera &amp; clara ſunt,</hi> &amp;c. but if theſe things be both true, and alſo clear; then without doubt, another ſenſe of the Apoſtle's words is to be ſought for. And they are to be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the number of thoſe, which S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith are hard to be underſtood: which men ought not to pervert to their own deſtruction, by endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from them (againſt the moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Teſtimonies of the Scripture) to make the moſt lewd people ſecure of obtaining Salvation, though they pertinaciouſly continue in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, not at all changed by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, or repentance.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">As for the true ſenſe of that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <pb n="115" facs="tcp:64584:62"/>though he ventures at it, yet he ſaith, in the next Chapter, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be informed by thoſe who are more learned and more underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>who can ſo expound it, as to let all thoſe things above mentioned remain true and unſhaken:</hi> in which the Scripture moſt openly avows that Faith profits Nothing, unleſs it be that, which the Apoſtle defines; that is, <hi>Faith which worketh by love:</hi> but without Works cannot ſave men, neither without fire, nor by fire.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Still he ſticks to this Rule, as moſt certain and unmoveable; that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſenſe be given of an obſcure Scripture, it contradicts not thoſe Scriptures, which are more plain: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe which teach us to live well, and ſhow the neceſſity of it; which none that love the Truth, as it is in Chriſt, will ever prejudice by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpertation of Scripture whatſoever.</p>
               <p>It is out of my way, to attempt the true meaning of the place now mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: having no other buſineſs in hand at preſent, but to ſhow that by adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as this Holy man did, to the evident Truths in the Scripture, they<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64584:63"/>will never permit us to put any bad and pernicious ſenſe, upon thoſe that are leſs evident. Let us ſtick, as he did, to this Rule; and we ſhall either put an harmleſs ſenſe upon them, or none at all.</p>
               <p>But then, we muſt, as I ſaid, be heartily in love with theſe plain Truths, and frame our lives accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them; for elſe we ſhall not uſe due care, not to croſs them in our Doctrine, if we croſs them in our Deeds: but rather be content that by falſe gloſſes upon other places, where the fraud will be leſs diſcernable, the Light of thoſe glorious Truths ſhould be obſcured, and the power and force of them enervated and broken. For what will not men ſay, and do, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves in their ſins, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the cleareſt Convictions of Gods Holy Word? which their bad aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions teach them to oppoſe; nay, make it their intereſt to reſiſt.</p>
               <p>And here it may be fit to take this occaſion, to give a few directions, for the right underſtanding of the Holy Scriptures: which if we obſerve, in our reading them, we ſhall not only<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64584:63"/>be preſerved from dangerous miſtakes, but reap great benefit by them. And I ſhall the rather do it, becauſe it will be a good introduction to the
<hi>Third</hi> Part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The firſt of them is a Rule, which is neceſſary in all Sciences, or parts of Knowledge; <hi>viz to learn ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie things firſt.</hi> We can have no ſound Underſtanding in the Scriptures, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we will follow their own Method; which is to learn firſt, to
<hi>fear God, and keep his Commandments;</hi> for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lies <hi>the beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> as he often tells us.</p>
               <p>It is againſt the very direction which the Scripture gives us, to be ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as to venture preſently into all the depths, that are in it; and to loſe our time in puzzling our minds to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the knots of difficult places. For they are not to be ſalved but by thoſe, who are well acquainted with what the Scripture principally aims at; which it teaches us in plain and eaſie words: and therefore they muſt be firſt learnt, as our Guides to thoſe things which are of higher contemplation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:64584:64"/>And he who is reſolved upon this Method, will find plain Truths enow to buſie and imploy an honeſt and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mind a long time: by which he is to prepare and ſit himſelf for more difficult inquiries; if it be needful for him to make them. Though the truth is, ordinary Capacities may ſafely paſs by thoſe things that are hard and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure; and content themſelves with the knowledge of eaſie and perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctrines, without any further ſearch: conſulting thereby beſt for their own eaſe and quiet, and for the Peace of the Church of God.</p>
               <p>And as for thoſe whoſe profeſſion it is, to devote themſelves to the ſtudy of all Holy Writ; even they muſt be ſure, for their own ſafety and others, to lay the Foundation well here, by thoroughly digeſting the Doctrines which are after Godlineſs, and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tincturing (as I may ſay) their minds therewith, before they meddle with other matters. For a ſenſe of true Goodneſs, will be as a Light to guide us in the interpreting thoſe things which ſeem dark, and need ſomething to illuſtrate them. And<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64584:64"/>what can we imagine that ſhould be, but ſomething contained in the ſame Book; even the true Light of Life, the Light which chaſes away all mens evil deſires, and the deeds of darkneſs; which makes the Soul pure, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice; which diſpoſes it to know God, and to love him, and to love all men for his ſake? This will inſtruct us how to interpret all the reſt; and not ſuffer us to entertain any ſenſe of them in our minds, which is repugnant to the Nature of God, and hinders the practice and increaſe of true Godlineſs, or prejudices Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and diſturbs Chriſtian Society: but conform all our thoughts unto a happy agreement with thoſe great and obvious Truths.</p>
               <p>Which therefore let us obſerve and mark, as the very Life and Soul of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; nay, let us imprint them on our minds, as the moſt neceſſary to be known, and remembred, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried conſtantly in mind, that we may never admit any thing to their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. For unleſs we be thus diſpoſed, we ſhall not only trouble our ſelves to no purpoſe, but confound all things;<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64584:65"/>and overturn the whole Frame of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. We ſhall be juſt like that Fool, whom <hi>Melancthon</hi> ſpeaks of, whoſe work it was to carry fuel daily to the Kitchin; and coming to a great Pile of Wood, where little pieces lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt, and the greateſt below, he would needs begin at the bottom: for which he gave this wiſe reaſon, That it was good to do the hardeſt work firſt, and then he ſhould be better able to deal with that which was eaſie. I need not make the application to thoſe who love to perplex themſelves with ſome deep, and I may ſay, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Points (if not well underſtood) before they are well ſtudied in the common Doctrines of Godlineſs, and have learnt what it is to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               <p>This is a prepoſterous courſe; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the clear light and guidance of the Holy Books; which teach us in the firſt place, to make this inquiry, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> And we are ſure none can be ſaved, but they who are obedient to the Lord Jeſus; whoſe Faith therefore teaches us to ſtudy his Precepts, before we meddle with other
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64584:65"/>matters. And theſe Precepts, as they are not grievous to thoſe that obey them; ſo they are not hard to be learnt in order to that obedience. But whatſoever concerns our Duty to God and Man, and the Duty of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon in the relation wherein they ſtand; of Parents and Children, Husbands and Wives, Maſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Princes and People, Teachers and Learners, are all, I have ſhown, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered here, with ſuch plainneſs and ſimplicity, that no Book in the World ever taught them in this manner. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe therefore, in all reaſon, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the common Principles of Chriſtian Faith, we muſt imploy our moſt earneſt care to ſettle them in our minds; and make them the Rule of all the reſt.</p>
               <p>But it is not enough to bring theſe things into our minds; I muſt add another Rule no leſs neceſſary than this: which is,</p>
               <p n="2">II. That <hi>to do what we know, is the way to know more what we have to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I have ſuggeſted already in the body of the foregoing Diſcourſe; and<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64584:66"/>therefore ſhall only commend the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious practice of one particular Duty: which is ſo frequently mentioned in the Holy Scriptures, that from thence we ought to conclude, it is of exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great moment It is, <hi>Humility; not to think of our ſelves more highly than we ought to think; nor to be wiſe in our own conceits: but to think ſoberly, and to be lowly in our own eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a number of Precepts of the ſame import with theſe: the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of which he ought to ſtudy dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and then heartily obey, who would advance to a higher degree of knowledge: for <hi>the meek</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the humble) <hi>will he guide in judgment: and the meek will he teach his way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man begin at firſt to think wrong of himſelf, he is not like to hit right in other things: but the eaſier miſtake in them, when he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſuch a cheat to be put upon him, as to have a vain opinion of himſelf; whom he hath better opportunities to be acquainted withal, than any thing elſe.</p>
               <p>And on the contrary, he that thinks right, in the firſt things he inquires<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64584:66"/>into; hath great incouragement and ſecurity to proceed, with hope of good ſucceſs in all that follows.</p>
               <p>It is true, when a man knows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he finds that he is a Creature apt to miſtake; prone to judge amiſs; forward to follow little fancies rather than reaſon, or reaſon dipt in paſſion and intereſt, and to forſake that which is pure and unbiaſſed.</p>
               <p>But this is ſo far from being a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement or hinderance to him, in ſearching after God's Holy Truth, that it is the very thing which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes him for it, and will ſecure him in it. For if he keep this humble ſenſe in his mind, how weak and frail a Creature he is, it will do him great ſervice; by preſerving him from raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in embracing any thing without great deliberation; and much more from haſtineſs, in venting any ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar conceit; and ſtill much more from pertinacity, in defending it, if it be vented; and moſt of all, from Faction and ſiding, and uncharitable cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and from that great danger of miſtaking, and never reforming an erroneous Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:64584:67"/>More particularly, in this buſineſs of reading the Scriptures, this humble ſenſe of his own weakneſs will,
<hi>Firſt,</hi> make him read them with greater care, attention and diligence; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring how prone he is to miſtake, even when he is very ſerious.</p>
               <p>And therefore, <hi>Secondly,</hi> it will make him diſtruſt his own beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, without Divine aſſiſtance: which he will pray and wait for, with an humility as great as the ſenſe of his unworthineſs to receive it.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it will diſpoſe him to liſten unto, and inquire after the ſenſe and judgment of other men, (whom he hath reaſon to think abler than himſelf) and to be willing to learn of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> And more particularly, incline him to follow the Guides of Souls: not with a blind obedience; but with a due attention to their dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and a great deference to their Judgment, and (where any doubt is publickly determined) a quiet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their Authority.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> (to name no more) content himſelf with plain, and ſafe,<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64584:67"/>and neceſſary things: at leaſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him from being too forward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be well prepared, to meddle with thoſe things which are not within every bodies reach.</p>
               <p>Now when we conſider all theſe bleſſed effects of
<hi>Humility,</hi> we cannot but ſay, it is a ſpecial means to attain the knowledge of Divine things, from God: who <hi>gives grace to the humble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St <hi>Auſtin</hi> was ſo ſenſible of this, that he adviſes <hi>Dioſcurus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> I VI.</note>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">not to think of any other way to attain the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, but that alone, which God himſelf, who knows how weak we are, and how apt to ſlip, hath chalkt out for us. <hi>Ea eſt autem prima humilitas, ſecunda humilitas, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia humilita</hi> &amp;c. And that way, is <hi>firſt</hi> Humility,
<hi>ſecondly</hi> Humility, <hi>thirdly</hi> Humility; and ſhouldſt thou ask me never ſo often about the way, I would give thee no other anſwer. Not that there are no other Precepts to be learnt, but unleſs Humility in all the good we do, do <hi>firſt</hi> go before, and <hi>ſecondly</hi> accompany, and <hi>thirdly</hi> follow after; pride and vain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64584:68"/>while we are pleaſing our ſelves in our good deed, will wreſt all the profit of it out of our hand, and make us loſe our labour. <hi>Vitia quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe caetera in peccatis, ſuperbia verò e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in rectè factis timenda eſt,</hi> &amp;c. For though we need fear no other vice, but when we do ill; yet this may ſteal upon us even when we do well: and great care muſt be uſed, leſt by the deſire of praiſe, we ſpoil thoſe actions which are really praiſe-worthy. Therefore as the nobleſt Orator, when he was askt, what he thought was chiefly to be obſerved in the Precepts of Eloquence, is ſaid to have anſwered, <hi>Pronunciation;</hi> and being askt what next, ſtill anſwered, <hi>Pronunciation;</hi> and the third time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing askt the ſame queſtion, again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied nothing but
<hi>Pronunciation:</hi> So as oft as thou ſhouldſt ask me of the Precepts of Chriſtian Religion, I would not think fit to anſwer any thing, but
<hi>Humility.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This wholeſome Humility then, which that our Lord might teach us, he humbled himſelf, let us carefully learn: yea, let us <hi>be clothed with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:64584:68"/>as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways carry in mind that of St. <hi>Paul, Knowledge puffeth up.</hi> There is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in reading and getting knowledge, unleſs Humility uſher it in, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon it, and perpetually go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it: for it will not miniſter to the nouriſhing of goodneſs; but to the feeding our ambition, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting contention, and inflaming of indiſcreet zeal, and thereby troubling the ſtate of God's Church. But Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is the Mother of meekneſs and peaceableneſs of Spirit; which is both moſt capable of wiſdom, and alſo moſt fit to communicate it unto others with advantage, and make it appear as lovely to them, as it is in its own nature.</p>
               <p>We have the Authority of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prophet for it in the place before mentioned, XXV. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. and of his great Son
<hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe Maxim this was, <hi>With the lowly is wiſdom,</hi> XI. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. and which is more than all, of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, who thanks his Heavenly Father (XI. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.) <hi>Becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent,</hi> that is, from
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64584:69"/>the ſelf-conceited Phariſees, <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them unto babes,</hi> ſingle-hearted and humble perſons: <hi>even ſo, Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight;</hi> this is moſt agreeable and pleaſing to the Divine Wiſdom, to communicate it ſelf, not to thoſe who think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wiſe, but to thoſe who are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſirous and ſtudious ſo to be.</p>
               <p>And ſo I proceed to a <hi>third</hi> Rule, which is a general one too, and ariſes from the former.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Which ſuppoſing that <hi>doing God's Will</hi> is the main thing at which a Chriſtian ought to aim, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from thence, that we ought to <hi>propound no other end to our ſelves in reading the Holy Books, but that we may thereby grow more holy, and be made perfect in every good work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this is certain, that if this be not always our end, we and theſe Holy Books do not deſign the ſame thing; and ſo we are never like to meet. Their deſign, it is viſible, is to <hi>make us wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> to <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us even as our Lord is pure,</hi> to help us to
<hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> If<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64584:69"/>we aim not therefore at this, they have nothing to ſay to us. If we lay aſide theſe thoughts, and divert to ſomething elſe in the ſtudy of the Scriptures, we ſhall wander in vain and unprofitable Speculations: and perhaps trouble the World, as well as our ſelves, with unneceſſary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines: which ingender ſtrife, and deſtroy Charity, and diſturb Peace, and turn men quite away from the practice of Piety.</p>
               <p>If we would be truly knowing, and thoroughly wiſe, with the Scripture-Wiſdom, we muſt ever draw all we know, and meet with there, unto this end: and not think we know it well, till we ſee how we may be made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereby.</p>
               <p>I cannot expreſs this in fewer or more proper words, than
<hi>Eraſmus</hi> hath done long ago, in more places of his Works than one; particularly in his Dedication of his Paraphraſe on St. <hi>Matthew</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the V.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">Since the Evangeliſts wrote the Goſpel to every body, I do not ſee why every body ſhould not read it. And I have ſo handled it, that<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64584:70"/>the moſt illiterate may underſtand it. Now it will be read with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt profit, if when any man takes it in his hand, it be with this mind, <hi>ut ſeipſo reddatur melior,</hi> &amp;c. that he may be rendred better than himſelf: and do not accommodate the Goſpel to his own affections, but correct his own life, and all his deſires by the Rule of the Goſpel.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I conclude this with that Saying of <hi>Seneca;</hi> In the ſame plat of ground, the Ox ſeeks for graſs, the Hound ſeeks for a Hare, and the Stork for a Snake: and juſt ſo it is with thoſe that read the ſame Scripture; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one ſeeks himſelf, and another ſeeks the World; one ſtudies, that is, to pleaſe himſelf with the Hiſtory of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Times, another to furniſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the knowledge that belongs to his Profeſſion; but he alone reads it as he ought, who therein ſeeks for God; and deſires to be <hi>filled with the knowledge of his Will, that he may walk before him in all well-pleaſing, being fruitful in every good work,</hi> I. Coloſſ. 9, 10.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:64584:70"/>IV. And whoſoever he is that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns this great End, and comes to learn to be good with an honeſt mind and heart, let him be careful to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve one Rule more; which is, <hi>To ſtudy and well digeſt the firſt Elements of Chriſt's Religion.</hi> For as he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read, nor write exactly, that doth not learn to ſpell truly; and he muſt underſtand ſyllables before he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands words and ſentences: ſo he will never find the ſaving Power of the Goſpel thoroughly working on his Spirit, that keeps not the firſt Truths always in his mind, and deeply root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Heart.</p>
               <p>The prime Principle of our Faith is, That <hi>Jeſus is the Son of God;</hi> that He ſpeaks from Heaven to us the uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Will of our Creator. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel will not have any efficacy upon us, unleſs we carry this along in our thoughts, when we apply our ſelves to ſtudy it; that this is the Voice of God, this is the Mind and Will of Him that made us; how ſhall we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, if we turn away from Him that ſpeaks from Heaven to us?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:64584:71"/>This if we carry in mind, while we read the Scriptures, they will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-awe us, and make us have Grace to <hi>ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear.</hi> We ſhall not dare to read them, as we do ſome humane Hiſtory, wherein we are not all concerned, but with attention, with ſeriouſneſs, and with diligence: tracing the Lord Jeſus, as pious Diſciples of his, in every ſtep; obſerving what he ſaid, and what he did.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">And thus ſeeking, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hunting after Him every where (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his words are in his Preface to his <hi>Annotations</hi> on the N. T.) we ſhall find in that moſt ſimple and rude Scripture, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable Counſel of celeſtial Wiſdom: we ſhall ſee in that fooliſhneſs of God (if we may ſo ſpeak) which at firſt ſight appears mean and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that which far excels all humane prudence, though never ſo ſublime and admirable.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And the next Principle is like to it; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Lord Jeſus will come to judge the World in righteouſneſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Gospel.</hi> This if we thought of, that we ſhall be judged,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:64584:71"/>and have Sentence paſſed upon us by this Rule; we could not but lay it to heart, and ſquare our life by it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let theſe firſt Principles of Faith be ſtrongly ſixed in our mind, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be in our thoughts: and let us think we have as much uſe of them, as he that reads hath of his Letters; which are the firſt Elements of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>Then for the Principles of Practice, this is the prime, the chief, the moſt fundamental in the whole Goſpel; <hi>He that will be my Diſciple, muſt deny himſelf, forſake all, and take up his Croſs and follow me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This our Saviour tells his Diſciples again and again, upon ſeveral occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, X. <hi>Matth.</hi> 38. XVI. 24. IX. <hi>Luke</hi> 23. XIV. 27, 33. In the laſt of which places, he lets them know, that it is as fooliſh to think of being a Chriſtian without learning this Leſſon, as it is for a man to begin the building of a Tower, before he hath computed the Charge; or for a Prince to undertake a War, without conſidering both his own force, and the ſtrength of his Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer. The ſenſe of which two Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles<pb n="134" facs="tcp:64584:72"/>our Lord ſumms up in theſe words; <hi>So likewiſe, whoſoever he be of you, that forſaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which few words, we have this account made to our hands (as a great Doctor of ours ſpeaks) that e're we can hope to be built up in the Faith of Chriſt, or ſafely ingage in the War againſt the Devil, the World and the Fleſh, we muſt make over our intereſt in all that is dear unto us here, and reſign it up to our Lord Chriſt: hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing ſo precious as his Love and his Salvation.</p>
               <p>That is the meaning of this Leſſon; We muſt not prize any thing ſo much, as the Mercy, Grace and Favour of God in Chriſt Jeſus. All the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments of this life, and life it ſelf, muſt not weigh ſo much with us, as God's good eſteem of us, his affection to us, the Honour, Glory and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality that Chriſt hath promiſed us.</p>
               <p>When we have once learnt this, and have it by heart, there will be no difficulty in learning all the reſt. The immediate reſult of it will be, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned<pb n="135" facs="tcp:64584:72"/>feigned aſſent to the truth and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all that Chriſt, the Prince of Life, hath revealed unto us; and an uniform obedience to his Holy Will in all things. For then there will be Nothing left to oppoſe him, Nothing to gainſay him; no intereſt, no head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong affection and deſire to reſiſt the impulſions of Divine Truth: whoſe natural property is, to incline and ſway the Soul to all kinds, and to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of true goodneſs.</p>
               <p>It is our duty then to ruminate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things over and over again, to repeat theſe Leſſons continually to our ſelves; till they become familiar to us, and have ſeated themſelves in our hearts: not thinking we know them, till we feel them; nor imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we feel them to purpoſe, till we be transformed into them.</p>
               <p>That is an excellent Saying of the Hebrews, <hi>He that learns the Law, and doth not repeat it, is like to him that ſows his ſeed, and never reaps, nor binds it into ſheaves, that he may carry it home into his Barn.</hi> And this; <hi>He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats his Leſſon an hundred times, is not ſo wiſe as he that repeats it an hundred times and one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:64584:73"/>Let us ever be telling our ſelves, that it is God who ſpeaks unto us by his Son, in theſe Holy Books; that this is the Rule of Life, whereby we muſt be judged; that we muſt ſtand or fall before God, according as we keep theſe Sayings; that Nothing is comparable to being beloved of God; Nothing ſo deſirable as to <hi>have our Faith found to honour, and praiſe, and glory at the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And then we ſhall deny our ſelves and our own deſires, commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and intereſts, that God's Will may be done by us: the whole World will ſeem inconſiderable in our eyes, and we ſhall eaſily forgo any thing that He will not allow us to keep: accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fundamental Rule of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; <hi>He that forſaketh not all that he hath, cannot be my Diſciple. And he that taketh not his Croſs, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after me, is not worthy of me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I conclude this Part of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, with the words of one of the Homilies of our Church: in the <hi>ſecond Part</hi> of the Exhortation to the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and knowledge of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures;</p>
               <p> 
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:64584:73"/>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">As concerning the hardneſs of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, he that is ſo weak, that he is not able to brook ſtrong meat, yet he may ſuck the ſweet and tender milk: and defer the reſt till he wax ſtronger, and come to more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. For God receiveth the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and unlearned, and caſteth away none, but is indifferent unto all. And the Scripture is full, as well of low valleys, plain ways, and eaſie for every man to uſe, and to walk in: as alſo of high hills and mountains, which few men can climb unto. And whoſoever giveth his mind to Holy Scriptures, with delight, ſtudy and burning deſire, it cannot be (ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>) that he ſhould be left without help.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">He that asketh ſhall have, and he that ſeeketh ſhall find, and he that knocketh ſhall have the door open. If we read once, twice, or thrice, and underſtand not, let us not ceaſe ſo, but ſtill continue reading, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, asking of others; and ſo by ſtill knocking, at the laſt the door ſhall be opened, as St.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:64584:74"/>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">Although many things in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture be ſpoken in obſcure Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rics; yet there is nothing ſpoken under dark Myſteries in one place, but the ſelf ſame thing in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is ſpoken more familiarly and plainly, to the capacity both of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and unlearned.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">And thoſe things in the Scripture, that be plain to underſtand, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Salvation, every mans duty is to learn them, to print them in memory, and effectually to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them. And as for the dark My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, to be contented to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in them, until ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe God to open them unto him: but not lay aſide the reading of the whole, becauſe of the darkneſs of ſuch places.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">And briefly to conclude (as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) by the Scripture all men may be amended, the weak be ſtrengthened, and the ſtrong be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. <hi>So that ſurely, none be Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mtes to the reading of God's Word, but ſuch as either be ſo ignorant, that they know not how wholeſom a thing it is: or elſe ſo ſick, that they hate the moſt <pb n="139" facs="tcp:64584:74"/>comfortable Medicine that ſhould heal them: or ſo ungodly, that they would wiſh the people ſtill to continue in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance of God.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:64584:75"/>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:64584:75"/>
            <head>PART III.</head>
            <p>I AM arrived now at the laſt of thoſe <hi>Three</hi> things I propounded, to be treated of in the beginning of this Book.</p>
            <p>That <hi>all who read the Scriptures are not in danger to wreſt them to their own hurt; but only the unlearned and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.</hi> Such men will wreſt them from their true meaning; but ſo they will other Diſcourſes, as well as the Scriptures; and the moſt clear and perſpicuous things, are liable to be perverted by them, as well as the diſſicult.</p>
            <p>In this we ſhall ſoon be ſatisfied, if we conſider briedy, whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> means, by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtable:</hi> which will alſo clearly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us, what courſe we are to take, that we may not wreſt the Scriptures, as ſuch men do.</p>
            <p>Now there is no great difficulty to know, who theſe are, if we mind the proper uſe of words, and the place where they are uſed.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:64584:76"/>
               <head>I. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NLEARNED.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND for the firſt of theſe, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned;</hi> the Apoſtle cannot be thought to have reſpect to ſuch as are ignorant in thoſe parts of Knowledge, which are now commonly called <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> (for ſo the Apoſtles themſelves were generally <hi>ignorant and unlearned,</hi> IV. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.) but to thoſe, who are ignorant of ſuch things as the Holy Scriptures treat of, and ought to be learnt by all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>This I think all will allow; and then they are more particularly meant, who are not skilled in the firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion. Men that know not, or mind not thoſe common <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Truths, upon which all Religion is built: nor are acquainted with thoſe plain unqueſtionable Principles of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> before mentioned in the Second Part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe I take to be the
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> here ſpoken of; who have not learnt ſo much as the firſt Elements, or (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks VI.
<hi>Heb.</hi> 1.) <hi>the word of the beginning of Chriſt:</hi> who want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:64584:76"/>the foundation of true Knowledge, will be apt to wreſt every thing they read, from its proper meaning.</p>
               <p>Such there were, even in the School of Chriſt, as St.
<hi>Paul</hi> himſelf teaches us, who were <hi>ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 Tim. III. 7. They frequented, that is, the Chriſtian Aſſemblies, where they received good Inſtructions: but their nanghty affections would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the known Doctrines of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to find entertainment in their minds.</p>
               <p>Which Doctrines are ſuch as theſe; That there is one God, who is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly juſt, and perfectly good, and knows the very thoughts of the heart, and changes not. And that He hath ſent Jeſus Chriſt, his only begotten Son, the Eternal Word, who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Worlds, to take our Nature upon him, to dye for our ſins, to riſe again, that he may be the Judge of all. And that He hath ſent the Holy Ghoſt from the Father, to teach us thoſe Rules of Faith and Holy life, whereby we ſhall be judged at the laſt Day: when he will raiſe up our dead<pb n="144" facs="tcp:64584:77"/>bodies; and give to thoſe who have done good, everlaſting Life; but ſend thoſe who have done evil, into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like, which depend on theſe, and are coherent with them, are the <hi>Chriſtian Learning:</hi> which they that did not know, and believe, and accordingly practiſe (as I ſhewed in the foregoing Diſcourſe) muſt needs be very great ſtrangers to the Holy Books; and be ſo far from reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any profit by them, that they would rather corrupt and abuſe them to the ſupport of their own uncertain, vain, or abſurd imaginations.</p>
               <p>Nor were they ſecure from this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger when they had learnt them; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they were likewiſe ſo fixed in their minds, that they were conſtantly guided by them. For the Apoſtle here teaches us, that not only the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtable</hi> alſo, wreſt the Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:64584:77"/>
               <head>II. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSTABLE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHO thoſe are is now eaſier to determine, if what hath been ſaid of the other, be admitted. They are ſuch as do not ſtedfaſtly believe what they have learnt: who having enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Truth, do not ſtick to thoſe Principles of Natural Light and plain Revelation, nor are ſetled in them; but ſometimes believe them, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times queſtion, or disbelieve them.</p>
               <p>Such perſons the ſame St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo deſcribes in the Chriſtian Church: who were <hi>toſſed up and down with every wind of Doctrine,</hi> and could ſix no where; but rolled in uncertainty, from one Opinion to another, till they loſt themſelves in Infidelity, IV.
<hi>Eph.</hi> 14. The Principles they had received were floating in their mind, and never came to any certain conſtant reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which made them apt, on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to pervert the Scriptures, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as their own Fancy, or the confident ſuggeſtion of ſome bold Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer, inclined them. For ſome men deliver the vaineſt Conceit, with ſuch<pb n="146" facs="tcp:64584:78"/>an aſſurance, and earneſt Zeal, that they may be well compared to a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent blaſt; which carries thoſe along with it, who are not ſetled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in their Belief.</p>
               <p>I may make many more words about this, but I ſhall ſcarce make it plainer; and therefore I will not endeavour it. But now deſire you to mind what courſe theſe words, thus explained, direct us to take; that we may be preſerved from abuſing the liberty we have of conſulting, on all occaſions, with the Oracles of God.</p>
               <p>There is ſome Learning, you ſee, required to the underſtanding of the Holy Scriptures. But you need not go far to ſeek it: for it conſiſts only in the knowledge of ſuch Natural Truths, as are ingraven upon our own minds; and of thoſe plain Doctrines of Chriſtianity, which are revealed in God's Word ſo clearly, that there is no Controverſie about them: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the great Deſign of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which St.
<hi>John</hi> expreſſes in this ſhort Sentence, <hi>Theſe things write I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that ye ſin not.</hi> This is very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and deep Learning, to know that<pb n="147" facs="tcp:64584:78"/>the firſt and chief End of Divine Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, is to teach us to live well: and the next follows in the next words of St.
<hi>John</hi> (1. II. 1.) <hi>If any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the righteous,</hi> &amp;c Be not diſcouraged, if contrary to the grent Deſign of Chriſtianity, you fall into ſin; but hope for Mercy through the Propitiation made by Chriſt Jeſus, who will intercede for the ſius of thoſe, who heartily make this their main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and buſineſs, not to ſin.</p>
               <p>Which Truths, of both ſorts, we muſt take ſome pains to ſix in our rainds, and root in our hearts; that our belief of them may not be ſhaken by any other perſwaſion whatſoever: much leſs by any ſudden conceit which ſtarts up in our minds, or is ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by others.</p>
               <p>And the way to do that, is to live by them: for nothing ſettles know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo much, as ſaithful practice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it; eſpecially when we are ſetled in this practice. For thoſe St.
<hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>unſtable Souls</hi> (in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter before this,
<hi>v.</hi> 14.) apt to be beguiled and inſnared; who had not
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:64584:79"/>arrived at a ſetled reſolution and an habitual courſe of well-doing.</p>
               <p>Now when this is done, which muſt be our firſt Work, there is but one Rule which I ſhall propoſe (becauſe, if well followed, it comprehends all in it) to make our reading the Holy Scriptures ſafe and ſecure. Which is this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Never to admit any Interpretation of Scripture from others, or faſten any ſenſe upon them our ſelves, which contradicts thoſe known Truths which we have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in which we are fixed, as the undoubted Mind and Will of God.</hi> They muſt be the meaſure of all the reſt: by them we muſt judge of all things, whether they be true or falſe, What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever overthrows them, and will not conſiſt with them, muſt be rejected: It muſt not make us doubt of them; but they muſt make us conclude, it is a ſafe Interpretation. And on the other ſide, whatſoever agrees with them, though it ſhould happen not to be the proper meaning of a place of Scripture into which we inquire, it can do no harm, if it be entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:64584:79"/>And here now I ſhall do theſe
<hi>three</hi> things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Show how we are to uſe this Rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> How neceſſary it is to keep to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How readily thereby we may ſalve many ſeeming difficulties in the Holy Scripture: at leaſt paſs by them ſafely, if we obſerve it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>Concerning the firſt, I ſhall only ſay theſe
<hi>two</hi> things.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we muſt <hi>never admit any Interpretation on a ſudden:</hi> till we have examined, how it agrees with the Principles of known and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Truth.</p>
                  <p>Fancy will be ſuggeſting things to us; and if we be not attentive, will ſometimes inſinuate very abſurd No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions into our Belief. Here therefore our care and labour is required, to bring along with us, to the reading of Holy Scripture, ſuch a ſenſe of God, and of our known Duty to him, and<pb n="150" facs="tcp:64584:80"/>of the end and intention of Religion, that it may be ready at hand, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our <hi>extempore</hi> conceits and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, which will be forward to miſlead us. And if they repreſent any thing to us, which makes Him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, or unmerciful; if they plainly lead us to negligence and careleſneſs in our Duty; if they ſtrike at the <hi>end of the Commandment,</hi> which is, <hi>Charity, out of a pure heart, and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and faith unfeigned;</hi> we muſt as ſuddenly lay them aſide, as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude themſelves upon us. For that cannot be the Mind of God, which croſſes the Natural Notions we all have of Him; or thwarts the plain Revelations He hath made of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Nature and Will; or tends to make us leſs diligent in his ſervice, leſs zealous of good works; unto which we <hi>are created</hi> and formed <hi>in Chriſt Jeſus, that we ſhould walk in them,</hi> II. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>And we are all concerned to watch carefully, leſt any thing of this kind inſinuate it ſelf, to the high diſhonour of Almighty God, and the infinite ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of our immortal Souls. And to<pb n="151" facs="tcp:64584:80"/>watch not only when we are reading the Holy Scriptures, but</p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> At all other times we muſt uſe due care, leſt our thoughts lead us to form any Opinions, which are contrary to the known Principles of Humanity, and Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p>The thoughts of men are reſtleſs; and are apt to caſt themſelves into a thouſand ſhapes, and frame innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable conceits. Now if we let any ſettle in our minds, which agree not with the Truths, I have often named; they will not fail to be intermedling when we read the Scriptures, and draw it to ſpeak in their favour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to its meaning. There is no private Opinion which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but we are naturally deſirous to have it juſtified and confirmed: and therefore we had need take care to entertain none that are inconſiſtent with Piety; for they will be ſure to catch at every word of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to give them countenance by its great Authority; and preſs it, againſt its will, to come to their ſervice. At every turn they will be interpoſing<pb n="152" facs="tcp:64584:81"/>their inclinations; and prove a biaſs upon our minds, to carry them aſide from the mark.</p>
                  <p>And the fuller we are of theſe, and the more deſirous to have them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; the more haſtily ſhall we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelves, that the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks in their favour: and proffers it ſelf as a Witneſs, to give Teſtimony to the truth of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits.</p>
                  <p>Let us provide therefore by a due vigilance and attentive conſideration, that they be not formed by our own private imaginations; but by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtanding Rule of natural Honeſty, Juſtice and Goodneſs; and by all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certain Principles ingrafted in us, or revealed to us: Which ſerve as an <hi>Index</hi> to point us which way our thoughts ſhould run; and where they ſhould ſix themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>THE neceſſity of which Care is the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing, I propounded to be briefly conſidered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:64584:81"/>And here <hi>two</hi> things more may be ſufficient to be duly weighed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That without this Care, the plaineſt Scriptures will be in danger to be perverted, as ſoon as the moſt difficult.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The very ſame places of Scripture will be liable to be ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully wreſted, to ſerve different pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſay the plaineſt Scriptures will be in danger to be perverted (and very dangerouſly too) as well as the moſt difficult. For it is not their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, that makes them be pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but mens own eaſineſs to believe any thing, which their private deſires would have to be true; though never ſo contrary to ſound Reaſon and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: which if they had regarded, would have directed them to make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſtruction of Holy Writings.</p>
                  <p>All the Metaphors, for inſtance, and reſemblances borrowed from things viſible, to repreſent the Glory of Chriſt's heavenly Kingdom, make the miſerable Jews (as their Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did before them) ſtill entertain<pb n="154" facs="tcp:64584:82"/>themſelves with pleaſant Dreams, of a glorious, pompous Monarchy here on Earth: though the Prophets, in as plain words as can be deviſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent Chriſt, their King, as a man of ſufferings, who ſhould endure grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indignities than any man ever did, and at laſt dye, and ſo riſe again, to ſit at the right hand of God, and give his Holy Spirit from thence, to fill all the Earth with the knowledge of the Lord; and thereby make them pious Subjects of a Divine Kingdom. This drowſineſs is ſo hereditary to their Nation, that they will not be awakened out of their ſlumber; by conſidering how much more the Soul is God's care, than the Body; and what the Prophets ſpeak concerning Chriſt's Government over mens minds and Conſciences, and the reformation He ſhould come to make in their life and manners.</p>
                  <p>Some Chriſtians have been deluded with the ſame Fancy; as if they had dreamt upon their Pillow.</p>
                  <p>But there are more palpable inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the abuſes committed among them, not by reading the Scripture<pb n="155" facs="tcp:64584:82"/>(for that they were not forbidden) but by not obſerving the Rule I am now eſtabliſhing. It was uſual for people, even in the ancient Times of Chriſtianity, to interpret the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture according to their fancy, mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſerve a preſent turn; juſt as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny make it do now. For
<hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, that they who, after their Converſion to Chriſtianity, ſtill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the trade of making <hi>Idols</hi> and
<hi>Images</hi> for the Heathen to Worſhip, defended themſelves (when they were reprehended for it) by a Saying in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> VII.
20. which they thus contracted, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fuerit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus, ita &amp; perſeveret;</hi> As every man is found, when he is called to Chriſtianity, ſo let him continue.</p>
                  <p>There is no man that reads what follows, but plainly ſees (if he be not reſolved to ſhut his eyes againſt all that contradicts his deſires) the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle deſigns Nothing, but that all men ſhould remain ſo well ſatisfied with the condition in which they were when converted to Chriſt; that if they were mere <hi>Slaves,</hi> they ſhould be content to continue ſo; and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part<pb n="156" facs="tcp:64584:83"/>from their Lords and Maſters, unleſs they would give them their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: which, he grants, was much to be deſired. But if the following words had not told us this is his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; yet the Rule before mentioned, would have ſufficiently ſecured them, from the ill uſe they made of his words: For as <hi>Tertullian</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves (in his Book of <hi>Idolatry, Cap.</hi> V. where he treats of this matter) it is an Interpretation, that directly leads to all wickedneſs.
<hi>Poſſumus igitur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in peccatis perſeverare ex iſta inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatione,</hi> &amp;c. as his words are: We may all then continue in our ſins, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Interpretation; for there is not one of us, who was not found a Sinner, when he was called into Chriſt's Service: who came down for no other reaſon, but to deliver us from our ſins.</p>
                  <p>But in the ſame manner they alſo abuſed, he obſerves there, ſome other Texts of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> wherein he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that
<hi>after,</hi> his Example, <hi>every man ſhould work and get his living with his own hands,</hi> 1 Cor. IV. 10. 2 Theſſ. III. 9, 10. By which Precepts, if all<pb n="157" facs="tcp:64584:83"/>that men wrought with their hands, might be defended; then Thieves and High-way men, and Coiners of falſe Money, and all other wicked perſons, would be juſtified by them, as well as theſe Image-makers, who alledged them. In a word,
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">let the Gate of the Church be ſet wide open, ſaith he, for all Comers, who live by their labour; if there be no exception of ſuch Arts and Trades, as the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of God doth not receive.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And indeed, the Scripture it ſelf teaches us this Truth, That it is not the difficult places only, which men wreſt to their deſtruction, but the plaineſt alſo, when thereby they can have ſome colour for their evil pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices. As for Example, what can be more certain than this, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle never gave any incouragement by his Doctrine for men to ſay, much leſs ſaid thus himſelf, <hi>Let us do evil, that good may come.</hi> That is, a good End will warrant evil Actions. And yet there were ſome, who were ſo auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as to affirm he taught this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: whom he contents himſelf to confute, with theſe few words, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:64584:84"/>vouchſafes them no other anſwer; <hi>Whoſe damnation is juſt,</hi> III. rom. 8. There was no ground, that is, for ſuch an interpretation of his words, but only their own evil Principles and Affections; which led them to make this Concluſion againſt the dictates of natural Reaſon and Chriſtianity: and therefore nothing could be ſaid for ſuch men; but they would pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; and Nothing was more juſt than that God ſhould leave them under Condemnation, who perverted holy Words to a meaning ſo croſs to all the known Principles of natural and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Truth, that Nothing could be more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Occumenius,</hi> upon this very Text of St.
<hi>Peter,</hi> gives another ſuch like inſtance, of wreſting St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s words, which, he ſaith, may ſerve inſtead of all.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">He having ſaid, V.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 20. <hi>Where ſin abounded, grace did much more abound;</hi> ungodly men pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſenſe, ſay, we have <hi>Paul</hi> on our ſide, who ſays, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Let us ſin the more abundantly, that we may be the more abundantly pardoned.</hi> Which <pb n="159" facs="tcp:64584:84"/>they do to their own deſtruction (ſaith St.
<hi>Peter</hi>) for they that killed the Prophets and the Apoſtles, and they that deſtrey and takeaway their words, by a perverſe interpretation, are obnoxious to one and the ſame Condemnation: becauſe they ſlew them, that the World might be no longer taught by them, the ſaving Truths of the Goſpel; and theſe in the like manner wreſt, or put upon the rack their words, that none by them may work out their Salvation.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, what is there clearer in the Apoſtolical Writings, than that they every where taught, God will raiſe the dead <hi>at the laſt day;</hi> in which He will judge the World in righteouſneſs. And yet there were thoſe who wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe words ſo foully, that ſome ſaid, the
<hi>Reſurrection was paſt already;</hi> of whom were <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> and
<hi>Philetas,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> II. 17, 18. and others ſaid, there was
<hi>no Reſurrection,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XV. 12. and others ſaid, Chriſt would never <hi>come again;</hi> but laught at his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of coming to reward the good, and at his threatnings of coming to puniſh the wicked, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us in this<pb n="160" facs="tcp:64584:85"/>very Chapter,
<hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>Knowing this first, that there ſhall come in the laſt days ſcoffers, walking after their own luſts,</hi> (there was the reaſon of their ſcoffing) <hi>ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? for ſince the firſt men fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the world.</hi> Which they would not have had the impudence to affirm (it being ſo eaſie to diſprove them) had they not affected (as he ſhows <hi>v.</hi> 5.) to be ignorant of what was as plainly recorded in the Holy Books, as any thing whatſoever; that there had already been, long ago, a great change made by the Flood, which ſwept away the World of the Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Which, if they had been ſerious, would have kept them from mocking, at another deſtruction threatned to the Wicked, with a promiſe of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the Godly, at our Saviour's ſecond Coming: and made them look upon what was paſt, as an Example of the like future Judgment.</p>
                  <p>I might give more numerous inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which would prove ſomething beyond this; that unpurged minds, or, which is all one, unlearned and<pb n="161" facs="tcp:64584:85"/>unſtable Souls, will not only wreſt plain Truths to ſerve their Luſts and Humours: but thereby be apt to grow more wicked, and more prejudiced againſt God and Goodneſs. For <hi>the opinion, or preſumption</hi> (as is excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved by a great Man) <hi>that any of our evil actions, or diſpoſitions, are countenanced from God's Word, doth mightily heighten them, in a degree of evil more than uſual.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The covetous, niggardly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful, for inſtance, if they pleaſe themſelves, in the precepts of frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and diligence; are exceedingly ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and rooted in thoſe ſins, with the pleaſure they take in their conceited conformity with the rule of Gods Word: which teacheth us to avoid Riot and Luxury, Sloth and Negligence. And thus the ſtubborn and ſelf-willed, are encouraged in their obſtinacy, by the commendations which are given to the conſtant and the well-reſolved. And the malicious, turbulent, and ſeditious Spirits, juſtifie their bitterneſs, fury, and contempt of Authority, from the examples of exceſſive zeal, or indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſwelling in Holy men upon juſt<pb n="162" facs="tcp:64584:86"/>occaſions, and that, perhaps, by a ſpecial Divine incitation; which is not by any man to be now imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>But it is time to leave this; and to give a ſhort account of the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. It is no leſs uſual, for want of obſerving this plain Rule, to preſs one and the ſelf ſame Scripture, to ſerve for different purpoſes: unto the great diſhonour of God, and of his Holy Oracles; which men, from hence, imagine have an uncertain found.</p>
                  <p>I might inſtance in ſome very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient abuſes of this nature; As that of our Saviour's, X. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>It is enough for the Diſciple, that he be as his Maſter,</hi> may be ſtrained to prove no body knows how many abſurdities. You may gueſs at the reſt by this one, that it was alledged by the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> to prove that Chriſtians ought to be circumciſed, becauſe Chriſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was (as
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members) and by the ſame reaſon may be urged to prove, that no Chriſtian ought to marry, becauſe Chriſt their Maſter never married.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:64584:86"/>But there are modern inſtances, more than enough, of this; ſuch as ſhow, that not only ignorant people, but the moſt inſtructed in humane Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wreſt the Scriptures notoriouſly, if they keep not cloſe to Principles of known Morality and Piety.</p>
                  <p>From thoſe two words, <hi>Paſce oves, Feed my ſheep,</hi> I know not how many things are endeavoured to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, by the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. If you ask how they prove the Popes Monarchy and Supreme Dominion in the Church, the Anſwer is, Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, Simon bar-Jona, Feed my ſheep; i. e.</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, regio more impera,</hi> command af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Regal manner. If you ask again by what Right he challenges to be the Supreme Judge in Controverſies of Faith, which anciently was thought to belong to General Councils out of the Word of God, the ſame Doctor tells you it is evident from the ſame words, <hi>Feed my ſheep.</hi> Hence he proves alſo his Infallibility, or that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not err in matters of Faith, becauſe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Feed my ſheep.</hi> Nay, by the ſame words, a <hi>fourth</hi> Prerogative<pb n="164" facs="tcp:64584:87"/>is eſtabliſhed, which is a power to make new Articles of Faith, if he think good. They are alledged alſo for a
<hi>fifth</hi> purpoſe, to prove that he hath a Treaſure made up of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt, and of the Saints, which he diſpenſes as he pleaſes to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; for ſo the ſame Doctor teaches in his Book of Indulgences, becauſe Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, Feed my ſheep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By which wonderful words alſo, he and others labour to prove, that the Pope can transfer Kingdoms, abſolve Subjects from the Oath of Allegiance, and depoſe them from their Thrones. And <hi>Becanus</hi> from the ſame words ſtill gathers, that he may inflict temporal Puniſhments, as they call them, not excepting death, upon thoſe Princes that are diſobedient to him.</p>
                  <p>So ſtrangely are men bent to force the meaning of Holy Writ, though they have never ſo good Parts, and great Learning; when they have once forſaken the guidance of Common Senſe, and the obvious Notions of Chriſtianity. Nay, the more witty they are, the worſe they are; if they have loſt their Conſcience, and keep<pb n="165" facs="tcp:64584:87"/>not ſtrictly to the firſt Principles of all Religion.</p>
                  <p>There is another Example to be given of this, of the ſame Nature. From thoſe words, <hi>Thou art Peter, and upon this Rock I will build my Church,</hi> &amp;c. one is content to prove no more but this, that the
<hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church cannot err:</hi> but another from hence affirms, that the <hi>Tradition of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church cannot err:</hi> which will not ſatisfie others, who conclude from the ſame words, that the <hi>Pope cannot err:</hi> and there are thoſe who alledge them to prove that a <hi>General Council cannot err.</hi> Theſe words cannot alike ſerve all theſe purpoſes (as our Divines right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have obſerved) for a Pope may err, where a Council doth not; and a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council may err, where the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church cannot. And therefore it is not the evidence of things, which leads men thus to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Holy Scriptures; but their own private affections, and their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral intereſts and deſigns, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of which they eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to apply them: Not attending to the clear ſcope of them; or rather<pb n="166" facs="tcp:64584:88"/>ſhutting their eyes, not only to that, but to the main ſcope of the whole Book of God, and to all other No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, which would give them better direction. And ſolve alſo, even ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeeming difficulties, which are in the Scripture; or, at leaſt, guide us ſo evenly, that we ſhall paſs ſafely by them.</p>
                  <p>Which is the <hi>third</hi> General Truth, I propounded in the beginning of this Part of my Diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>AMONG all thoſe things, which we are concerned to learn, there are none thought more difficult than ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral paſſages in St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles: ſome part of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had in his eye, when he concluded his Second Epiſtle. But I may be confident, that if we will admit, or take up, no ſenſe of them, that is contrary to ſuch known and confeſſed Truths, as are on all ſides embraced, we may give a fair account of them; at leaſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our ſelves from making any dangerous conſtruction of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:64584:88"/>That which above all the reſt is thought to be of greateſt difficulty, is his <hi>Doctrine of Election and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> which ſome take to be the <hi>things hard to be underſtood</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. But if we ſtick cloſe to the known fixed Principles of Reaſon and Religion, which are naturally writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on our Hearts, or revealed by our Saviour, we ſhall be led thereby unto a fair and eaſie interpretation of his meaning in theſe matters.</p>
                  <p>For there is an Election of whole Nations, and there is an Election of particular Perſons: and they are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted either to enjoy the means of Grace, or to partake of Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, it is evident, are abſolute, and have no dependence upon any thing we do: but the latter are not; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly teaches us, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> II. 13. where he ſaith, God had <hi>choſen them to Salvation, through Sanctification of the Spirit, and belief of the Truth.</hi> Faith was ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to this, and the fruits of Faith, in Sanctity and Holineſs. They were not choſen to Salvation but through<pb n="168" facs="tcp:64584:89"/>theſe; though they were choſen to be made partakers of the Grace of the Goſpel before theſe.</p>
                  <p>The like may be ſaid concerning <hi>Reprobating,</hi> or rejecting men. Which ſometimes plainly concerns whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and ſometimes particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: and ſometimes is only from the Priviledges they formerly enjoyed; ſometimes from Eternal Life; both of them for their ſins; and the former (the National rejection from their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Priviledges) is deſigned by God to prevent the latter; <hi>viz.</hi> the final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of every one of them, which he doth not deſire.</p>
                  <p>Thus God reprobated, or rejected and caſt away
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches in the Epiſtle to the
<hi>Romans:</hi> But it was not with an intention that they ſhould utterly periſh. No, he ſaith more than once, <hi>God forbid: i. e.</hi> he abhorred ſuch a thought; he diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any ſuch meaning. For, quite contrary, by their being rejected from enjoying the Priviledges they former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had, the Gentiles were brought to Chriſtianity: and the end of that, was to
<hi>provoke the Jews alſo to jealouſie;</hi>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:64584:89"/>and move them at laſt to bethink themſelves better, and to repent of their ſin and be ſaved</p>
                  <p>Let any man read ſeriouſly the <hi>Tenth</hi> and
<hi>Eleventh</hi> Chapters of that Epiſtle, and he will be ſatisfied that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation ſpoken of in the <hi>Ninth</hi> Chapter, was ſuch; that they might notwithſtanding be reſtored into the favour of God, and be finally ſaved. That is, they were rejected from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his peculiar people, as they had been: but not from all hope of his Mercy, if they did not continue
<hi>a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient and gainſaying people.</hi> For the Apoſtle ſtill prays for them, in the entrance of the <hi>Tenth</hi> Chapter: and begins the
<hi>Eleventh</hi> in this manner, <hi>I ſay then, Hath God caſt away his people? God forbid.</hi> That is, will any man infer then, from what I have ſaid, that God hath utterly reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, never to receive them more? No ſuch matter; none ought to interpret my words to ſuch a ſenſe; which I diſown; nor did it ever come into my mind. For I my ſelf am an inſtance of the contrary; being <hi>an Iſraelite, of the ſeed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:64584:90"/>And yet he ſaith afterward, that
<hi>God had blinded their eyes, and given them a spirit of ſlumber, eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and ears that they ſhould not hear; according to that of David, Let their table be made a ſnare and a trap and a ſtumbling-block,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>But what then? <hi>Have they ſtumbled that they ſhould fall,</hi> and be utterly ruined? <hi>God forbid: but rather through their fall Salvation is come to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, to provoke them to jealouſie, v.</hi> 11. For if they did not abide ſtill in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, he ſhows they might be graft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Church again, <hi>v.</hi> 23. And explains his mind ſtill more fully in this matter, <hi>v.</hi> 25. that <hi>blindneſs was hapned</hi> only <hi>in part to Iſrael,</hi> till the fulneſs of the Gentiles was come in: <hi>and ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For though they were, as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel, Enemies for our ſake; yet, as touching the Election, they were beloved for the Fathers ſake. They were not abſolutely and finally reprobated; but for the preſent did not believe, that through the Mercy ſhowed to us Gentiles, they might<pb n="171" facs="tcp:64584:90"/>alſo obtain Mercy. For God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded them all in Unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all, <hi>v.</hi> 28, 31, 32.</p>
                  <p>All theſe expreſſions, and a number more in that Chapter, evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, it was not an irrecoverable Rejection, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of; much leſs a Rejection without any reſpect to their ſins; but ſuch a Rejection for their rejecting Chriſt, as in the deſign of God, was to bring them to Repentance, and to Faith in Chriſt; when they ſaw what they had loſt (and others had gained) by their Infidelity.</p>
                  <p>He now that will interpret the <hi>Ninth</hi> Chapter, according to the plain, declared ſenſe of the Apoſtle in this, will have no hard work to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake: but eaſily ſee that as he ſpeaks of the whole body of the Jewiſh Nation, ſo he did not think them to be utterly loſt; but deſigned even their Reprobation for their recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                  <p>And now I might proceed to ſhow (if it would not inlarge this Treatiſe too much) how the difficulties which<pb n="172" facs="tcp:64584:91"/>are raiſed about Faith and Works, are not ſo great neither as they ſeem; if we firmly adhere to common Truths. Which lead every man to conclude, that the Faith which enters us into a ſtate of Juſtification, doth include in it an hearty purpoſe of well-doing: and that, being thus entred, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not continue in that ſtate, unleſs (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our holy purpoſe) we bring forth the fruit of good Works.</p>
                  <p>And, in like manner, what he ſaith of <hi>God's hardening mens hearts,</hi> is not difficult to be underſtood by thoſe, who are not unlearned and unſtable: but are skilful in the Principles of natural Knowledge and of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and who are rooted in them ſo, that they hold them faſt, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcever expreſſions there may be, that ſeem to contradict them.</p>
                  <p>But it is time to draw towards a Concluſion of this Treatiſe; which ſhall end as it began. The Doctrine of this Church, it appears, is moſt pure and ſincere in this Point; and moſt conformable to what we find de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the holy Doctors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, in the beſt Ages. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<pb n="173" facs="tcp:64584:91"/>no Member of it ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, for any reaſon, to lay aſide the reading of the Holy Scriptures; when there is a more pious courſe to which they themſelves direct us. Which is, to learn thoſe things well, which we cannot miſapprehend, if we mind them; and which will keep us from miſapprehending all other things, if we ſtick to them, and will not deſert them.</p>
                  <p>Let that be your firſt buſineſs, to learn all
<hi>General</hi> Truths, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the <hi>Particular</hi> in them. And when you have learnt them, receive no particular Opinion, which croſſes thoſe general Truths; for you may be ſure it is falſe: becauſe one Truth cannot croſs another; and all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions muſt be judged by the prime Truths, which ought to ſtand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable.</p>
                  <p>But above all, let us eſtabliſh thoſe Truths in our minds and hearts, which teach us to be good. For there is no Diſpute about this, that we ought to be devoutly Religious, and ſober, and juſt, and temperate in all things: meek alſo, humble, patient, ready
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:64584:92"/>to do good, and to forgive. And if we exerciſe our ſelves continually in the practice of theſe, and ſuch like Vertues, which are evidently taught us in the Holy Books; they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from making any ill uſe of any thing we read there: and teach us to turn all we read, into our nouriſhment and increaſe in true Godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>Hear the Firſt <hi>Homily</hi> of our Church; in the concluſion of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In reading God's Word, he moſt profiteth not always, that is moſt ready in turning of the Book, or in ſaying of it without Book; but he that is moſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into it, that is moſt inspired with the Holy Ghoſt, moſt in his heart and life altered and changed into that thing which he readeth: he that is daily leſs and leſs proud, leſs wrathful, leſs cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and leſs deſirous of worldly and vain pleaſures: he that daily (for ſaking his old vicious life) increaſeth in Vertue more and more. And to be ſhort, there is nothing that more maintaineth Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, and driveth away <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, than doth the continual reading or hearing of God's Word; if it be joyned with a godly mind, and a good<pb n="175" facs="tcp:64584:92"/>affection, to know and follow God's Will. For without a ſingle eye, pure intent, and good mind, nothing is allowed for good before God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>THE great Objection againſt all that hath been ſaid is, That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe Directions, Lay-men, we ſee, do abuſe the Holy Scriptures; and which is more, the reading of them hath bred infinite Hereſies: and therefore the ſafeſt courſe is to forbid them to be read by the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>ANSWER</hi> I.</head>
               <p>TO the firſt part of which, an Anſwer hath been returned already, That there is nothing in the World ſo uſeful and neceſſary, but it is liable to be abuſed; and yet it muſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be kept out of the hands of vulgar people, for their common benefit. What more uſeful, nay neceſſary than fire; and yet malicious, or negligent people, may burn the beſt houſe that<pb n="176" facs="tcp:64584:93"/>is with it, which they ſhould only warm.</p>
               <p>But beſides this, I have one ſhort Reply more to make: That none have been more guilty of abuſing the Holy Scripture, than they who ought to have been Guides to the Church and People of God, by a ſound interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof. Examples of which I am not diſpoſed to name, unleſs any ſhall be ſo untoward as to deny it: and then a great many may be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, like to that of him, who becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid,
<hi>If a beaſt touch the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, let it be ſtoned,</hi> concluded that no ſimple or unlearned man, ought to preſume to meddle with the ſublimity of the Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>A hard caſe this, that vulgar people ſhould be treated like Beaſts: but thus Learned men will miſinterpret Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, when they are inclined only to ſerve their Cauſe; and be as forward (if they be not diſintereſſed) to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead the people, as the people are to miſlead themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:64584:93"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ANSWER</hi> II.</head>
               <p>TO the other part of the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſhall give ſomething fuller ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</p>
               <p n="1">I. And firſt of all, it is not true that all Hereſies have ſprung from mens reading the Scriptures, or from their miſunderſtanding them: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from their not reading them, as St.
<hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> you have heard, was of opinion; whoſe words I have quoted more than once, in the firſt Part of this Diſcourſe. Which are of the ſame import with thoſe of our Saviour, XXII. <hi>Matth.</hi> 29. <hi>Ye do err, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, and the power of God.</hi> That is, not being acquainted with what natural Reaſon taught concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Omnipotency, as well as what the Scripture taught about the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Here it may be fit to obſerve theſe four things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Fathers obſerve, all the ancient Hereticks did not read the Scripture. They are the words of<pb n="178" facs="tcp:64584:94"/>St. <hi>Auſtin, Lib.</hi> III. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>De Geneſi ad literam. For neither do all Hereticks read the Catholick Scriptures: nor are they Hereticks for any other reaſon, but becauſe they not underſtanding them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, pertinaciouſly aſſert their own falſe Opinions againſt their Truth.</hi> And thus St. <hi>Hierom</hi> in the laſt words of his Commentary upon the VII. of <hi>Hoſea. All the queſtions of the Hereticks and of the Gentiles are the ſame; becauſe they follow not the Authority of the Scriptures, but the ſenſe of humane Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They obſerve, that the men who pretended moſt to this, were the Original of Hereſies, <hi>viz.</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. Thus <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his firſt Book againſt
<hi>Marcion,</hi> ſpeaking of the Profeſſors of Wiſdom, ſaith, <hi>De quorum ingeniis omnis haereſis anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> From whoſe Wits all Hereſie is begotten and incouraged. And more fully in his Book <hi>of Preſcriptions,</hi> Cap. 7.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">
                     <hi>Ipſae deni<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> haereſes à Philoſophia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimantur,</hi> Hereſies themſelves had life given them from Philoſophy. For the <hi>Aeones</hi> came out of the School of <hi>Plato: Marcion's</hi> God came from the <hi>Stoicks:</hi> and the Souls Mortality <pb n="179" facs="tcp:64584:94"/>from the <hi>Epicureans:</hi> and the denial of the Reſurrection of the Body, was taken from one School of all the Philoſophers. And ſo he proceeds, ſhowing how the <hi>Fables,</hi> the
<hi>endleſs Genealogies,</hi> the <hi>unprofitable queſtions,</hi> and
<hi>Diſputings</hi> mentioned in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, came out of the ſame Forge: and that the Apoſtle takes notice of it, when he gives the
<hi>Coloſſians</hi> a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat</hi> againſt <hi>vain</hi> Philoſophy, II. <hi>Col.</hi> 8.</q> From whence we may note, that the Scriptures themſelves aſſign the Original of Hereſies, and teach us to beware of it; ſo far are they from leading us into them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And there is a <hi>third</hi> Cauſe of them mentioned in Scripture alſo, <hi>viz. the Traditions of men,</hi> VII.
<hi>Mark</hi> 7, 8. And thus <hi>Firmilian</hi> obſerves in his Letter to St.
<hi>Cyprian,</hi> That <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>Cerdo,</hi> a great while after the Apoſtles, <hi>induxit ſacrilegaem adverſus Deum traditionem,</hi> brought in a ſacrilegious Tradition againſt God:
<hi>Apelles</hi> alſo, conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Blaſphemy, added <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta alia nova,</hi> many other Novelties; which were more grievous, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:64584:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>oppoſite to Faith and Truth. And ſo did
<hi>Valentinus</hi> and <hi>Baſilides,</hi> who rebelled againſt God's Church, by their wicked Forgeries.</p>
               <p>And thus St. <hi>Hierom</hi> introduces He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks maintaining their Errours, in the very Dialect of the now <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors; <hi>We are the Sons of thoſe wiſe men, who from the beginning delivered unto us the Apoſtolical Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lib.</hi> VII. <hi>in Eſaiam, Cap.</hi> XIX. But S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> every where appeals from all pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tradition whatſoever, unto the Dictates of our Lord and his Apoſtles,
<hi>i. e.</hi> unto Scripture-Tradition. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, in that famous Epiſtle of his to <hi>Pompeius; All religious and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple minds have a compendious means, both to lay aſide Errour, and to find out Truth:</hi> nam ſi ad divinae traditionis caput &amp; originem revertamur, ceſſat error humanus; <hi>for if we go back to the Head and Original of Divine Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, there is an end of humane Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi> And a little after, he tells us what he means by this Divine Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when he ſaith, <hi>If there be any doubt, any wavering about the Truth, let us return,</hi> ad originem Dominicam,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:64584:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; Evangelicam &amp; Apoſtolicam Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem,
<hi>to our Lord's Original, or beginning, both the Evangelical, and Apoſtolical Traditions:</hi> that is, to the Doctrines delivered in the
<hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pels,</hi> and in the Writings of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Another Spring of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie were pretended Revelations. Thus the <hi>Cataphrygae,</hi> as the ſame <hi>Firmilian</hi> tells us; <hi>&amp; novas Prophetias uſurpare conantur,</hi> endeavoured alſo to make uſe of new Prophecies. And a little after, <hi>We know they cannot have Chriſt, who challenge to themſelves their falſe Prophecy, againſt the Faith of Chriſt.</hi> And whence they had their Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who, in the boſom of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, invented a <hi>Fifth Goſpel</hi> (which threatned the overthrow of our <hi>four</hi>) is not hard to reſolve. Not out of the Holy Scriptures, we may be ſure: and therefore the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way them from the people, will not prevent all Hereſies; but they will ſtart up, as they have done, from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cauſes: and they will the ſooner ſtart up, if the Scriptures be neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:64584:96"/>II. But I deſire it may be further. conſidered, that as Hereſies will ſpring up from other Cauſes, though men do not read the Scriptures: ſo <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> have not been always the Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of them; but they to whom none deny the liberty of reading the Holy Books. For the moſt pernicious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, that have been in the Church, had their beginning from Prieſts; as appears by <hi>Arius</hi> and
<hi>Neſtorius.</hi> And indeed no man can frame an Hereſie, but he that is of excellent Parts, as St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s opinion is; whoſe words are theſe upon the X. of <hi>Hoſea.</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">No man can deviſe and ſet up a Hereſie, but he that is <hi>ardentis ingenii,</hi> of an extraordinary Wit; and hath gifts of Nature, created by God the great Artificer: ſuch was <hi>Valentinus,</hi> ſuch was <hi>Marcion;</hi> whom we read to have been moſt learned; ſuch was <hi>Barde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanes,</hi> whoſe Wit the Philoſophers themſelves admired.</q> And therefore, either the Scriptures muſt be wholly laid aſide, the greateſt men, for Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Parts, being apt to abuſe them, if they be not humble and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:64584:96"/>good: or men muſt be taught how to prepare themſelves for the reading of them, and what to ſeek for there; and then any body may ſafely take them into their hands, and make them their conſtant Companions.</p>
               <p n="3">III. It muſt likewiſe be further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that there is ſomething elſe to be feared beſide Hereſie; and that is ſtupid ignorance, or groſs Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: which, Experience ſhows us, have followed upon the taking the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures from the people; even as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs comes and covers the Earth, when the light is withdrawn from it. And ought we not, in all reaſon, to be as ſtudious and ſolicitous, to prevent theſe, as to prevent Hereſie? Since they are no leſs dangerous, or rather more dangerous by far: even for this reaſon, becauſe they make men liable to fall into the moſt ſottiſh Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; if not into down-right Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; which is a worſe thing than He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
               <p>How <hi>Images</hi> came to be Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Books, it is needleſs to relate (the matter being very plain) and<pb n="184" facs="tcp:64584:97"/>how
<hi>Image-Worſhip</hi> thence aroſe; and how fatal this hath been to the vulgar people, I have not room to diſcourſe: nor how <hi>Legends of Saints</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, full of abſurd and incredible ſtories, which have diſgraced the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſtianity, and tempted many to disbelieve the true Hiſtory of our Saviour's and his Apoſtles Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Operations. But this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that they were deviſed to ſupply the place of the Holy Scriptures; that the people might have ſomething to entertain them, when they were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from them. It was the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, at leaſt, of that; theſe fabulous ſtories being recommended to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples affection, when they were fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from medling with the Bible, as a dangerous Book: nay, when it's cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit was diſgraced by many words of reproach. Which we in this Church think our ſelves bound to wipe off, by recommending it to the peoples beſt affection and conſtant peruſal; as a means to preſerve them from ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ignorance, and ſtupid Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and all vain Superſtitions, and falſe Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:64584:97"/>IV. Nor is it eaſie for our people by this means to fall into Hereſie; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have the liberty of reading the Scriptures, but interpreted to them by the Miniſtry of the Church (whereby they are taught continually to have recourſe to their Paſtors) and by ſundry Tracts, Expoſitions, and Paraphraſes, allowed by publick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: Particularly, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation, care was taken that <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his Paraphraſe, ſhould be placed in every Pariſh-Church of the Realm; in which he doth not follow his own private Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but, like a truly great Man, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the ſenſe of the ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Now if after all this, men do fall into Hereſie, it muſt be imputed to ſome other Cauſe, than their read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures. For if they had minded them, they would have learnt to be humble, modeſt, peaceable, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable to their Guides; and to take heed of thoſe who cauſe Diviſions, and are proud, and dote about Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions<pb n="186" facs="tcp:64584:98"/>and ſtriſes of Words; and that creep into houſes to inſtill private Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and, very frequently, lead men from the Scriptures, to pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Revelations or Traditions. That is, they would not have faln into any ſort of Hereſie; but kept <hi>unto the wholeſom words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Doctrine which is according unto Godlineſs.</hi> Unto which, if men will not attend, there is no remedy; they will fall into Hereſies, or worſe; whether they read the Scriptures, or read them not. The Scripture it ſelf tells us as much, that <hi>there muſt be Hereſies,</hi> 1 Cor. XI.
19. that is, God will not hinder it, unleſs men will be guided by him, and be truly good: But he hath a very good end, as it there follows, in permitting it; which is, that it may be manifeſt, who are honeſt-hearted Chriſtians, ſincerely in love with Truth and Goodneſs, and who are not.</p>
               <p>And that muſt be the care of every good man, not to take or throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Scriptures, to prevent Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: but, if Hereſies do ariſe, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour (according to the direction<pb n="187" facs="tcp:64584:98"/>of the Scriptures) to approve his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity unto God, by ſtedfaſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in Faith and Holineſs.</p>
               <p>And after the ſame manner muſt he govern himſelf, if the Guides of his Soul do not perform their Duty. Which I ſhall repreſent in the words of <hi>Eraſmus;</hi> out of his <hi>Preface</hi> to the Reader, before his Annotations on the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">It is the Paſtors Office to diſtribute the Bread of Life to the people. But what if they do not their Duty? What muſt the people do?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">They muſt implore the help of the Supreme Paſtor Chriſt Jeſus; who ſtill lives, and hath not forſaken the care of his Flock: But being ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the publick Prayers of his People, will do what is promiſed in <hi>Ezekiel; Behold, I will both ſearch my ſheep, and ſeek them out. As a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd ſeeketh out his flock, in the day that they are ſcattered: ſo will I ſeek out my ſheep, and will deliver them out of all places, where they have been ſcattered in the cloudy and dark day;</hi> with all the reſt that there follows XXX.
<hi>Ezek.</hi> 12, 13, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:64584:99"/>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">The vulgar people are Sheep; but endued with reaſon: and out of thoſe Sheep are Paſtors made. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it falls out, that a Sheep may know more than his Paſtor. As a Lay-man therefore ought not ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to rebel againſt the Prieſts, leſt that order be confounded, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have in the Body of Chriſt: ſo the Prieſts ought not to exerciſe Tyranny over the Flock of Chriſt; for if they do, the Sedition will lye at their door.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">When the Paſtors do their duty, they are to be reverently heard as Angels of God, by whom Chriſt ſpeaks to us. And when they teach unſincerely, the people muſt pick out all that's good, if there be any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it. But if they teach not at all, or teach thoſe things that are plainly repugnant to the Goſpel, let every man refreſh his Soul with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reading. And Chriſt, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to be preſent when two or three are gathered together <hi>in his Name,</hi> will not be wanting, by his Spirit, to one Soul that meditates piouſly in his Holy Word.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:64584:99"/>
                  <q rend="inline margSglQuotes">In vain are ſix thouſand gathered together, if it be not <hi>in his Name.</hi> Now they are gathered together in Chriſt's Name, who have reſpect to Nothing but his Glory, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation of their Souls.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>I ſhall conclude all with the ſenſe of that great Man, St.
<hi>Athanaſius:</hi> who wrote a little Treatiſe on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to reprove the audaciouſneſs (as he calls it) of thoſe, who ſaid that it was needleſs to look into the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; and bad men <hi>not to ſearch into them, nor to ſpeak out of them, but</hi> to content themſelves with the Faith they had <hi>received. For ſearching into the Scriptures,</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>doth but make things more obſcure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which he replies many things, which I might digeſt into Heads; but I ſhall preſent them to the Reader juſt as they lie in the
<hi>Second Tome</hi> of his Works, <hi>pag.</hi> 295. of the <hi>Paris</hi> Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, MDCXXVII.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This very Aſſertion,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhows the inconſiſtency of their Doctrine, and<pb n="190" facs="tcp:64584:100"/>that it hath Nothing to ſupport it.</hi> He means, they would not be afraid men ſhould ſearch into the Scriptures, if they thought, what was taught by them, would be there juſtified.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we truſt to the truth of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Scripture) <hi>and to the help of him who cannot lye, who ſaith,</hi> Every one that ſeeks ſhall find.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore we ſeek as we ought; and we find what we ought; and we speak with demonſtration; and we hear with a genuine intention: that we may perſwade our domeſticks; and that we may confute our Adverſaries; and that we may by our ſearch be gainers our ſelves; and not propound any thing that is inconſiſtent unto others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Would you have me neglect the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures? Whence then ſhould I have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? Would you not have me to mind knowledge? But whence then ſhould I have Faith?</hi> Paul <hi>cries,</hi> How ſhould they believe unleſs they hear? <hi>And again,</hi> Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. <hi>He then who forbids the Word, obſtructs hearing, and throws out Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No man can be ignorant of the Roman<pb n="191" facs="tcp:64584:100"/>Laws</hi> (being a Member of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire) <hi>without danger. They then who forbid us to ſtudy and learn the great Oracles of the King of Heaven, what kind of miſchief do they not craftily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive againſt us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scripture is the food of the Soul. Ceaſe then, O man, to ſtarve the inward man, and to kill it with hunger: intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a famine, not of bread nor of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but of hearing the Word of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is one that inflicts wounds; and doſt thou forbid the application of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines? For ſhame do not talk, as if the various wiſdom in the Books of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, were vain and to no purpoſe.</hi> One may as well, he means, bid people not mind their Preſcriptions, though there be many Diſeaſes in the World, as not read the Scriptures, when their Souls are in danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reverence that Lover of God's Word, the Eunuch: who did not neglect reading upon the road. Whoſe good intentions our Lord accepting, ſent him ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way an Inſtructer; who made him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what he read, and, by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, brought him to his Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:64584:101"/>
                  <hi>Hence it is that our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> Search the Scriptures: <hi>by ſearching, meaning careful and ſober inquiry into hidden things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Out of the Scriptures, is the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of things obſcure; the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hope; the event of promiſes; the finding of our Saviour: according to that,</hi> We have found Him, of whom
<hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets wrote.</p>
               <p>Paul <hi>himſelf uſes Scriptures for the eſtabliſhment of the Truth. And if he that heard ineffable things, he that was thoroughly inſtructed in ſecrets, he that had Chriſt ſpeaking in him, doth not ſimply uſe his own private Authority, without the teſtimony of the Scriptures: how can we with ſafety now neglect the Divine Legiſlation, and ſpeak what we think good out of our own hearts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But there are ſome things tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Conceptions. I ſay ſo too: and this we learn out of the Scriptures; that we may underſtand what things are fit for us to ſeek after, as being attainable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For it is neither pious to venture upon all things: nor is it conſiſtent with Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to neglect all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What we worſhip, we ought all to be</hi>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:64584:101"/>
                  <hi>acquainted withal: according to that which is written,</hi> We know what we worſhip. <hi>But how great, or what kind, or after what manner, or where, it is the part of mad-men to inquire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that would have none to judge of their Doctrines but themſelves, deter men from reading the Scriptures; preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is immodeſt to pry into ſuch inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible things: but in truth, fearing to be convinced out of them, of holding bad Opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I omit the reſt, which is but little more than I have repreſented; and ſhall end all with his words to <hi>Maca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> in the very beginning of his Works, againſt the Gentiles; <hi>The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and divinely inspired Scriptures, are ſufficient of themſelves for the declaration of the Truth; and there are many Books compoſed about the ſame things, by our Teachers of bleſſed Memory: Which if any man peruſe, he will know, in ſome meaſure, the meaning of the Scriptures, and be able to attain the knowledge he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Third Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64584:102"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Books written by the Reverend Doctor <hi>Patrick.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>THE <hi>Chriſtian Sacrifice;</hi> A Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſhewing the Neceſſity, End, and Manner of receiving the Holy Communion: Together with ſutable Prayers and Meditations for every Month in the Year; and for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Feſtivals in Memory of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour. In Four Parts. The Eighth Edition corrected, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Devout Chriſtian inſtructed how to pray and give thanks to God:</hi> Or, A Book of Devotion for Families, and particular perſons, in moſt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Humane Life. The Fifth Edition, in
<hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Advice to a Friend. The Fourth Edition, in
<hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Jeſus and the Reſurrection, juſtified by Witneſſes in Heaven and in Earth. In Two Parts, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64584:102"/>
               <item>The Book of <hi>Job</hi> Paraphras'd, in
<hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> Paraphras'd, in
<hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Truth of Chriſtian Religion, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Glorious Epiphany, with the Devout Chriſtians Love to it, in <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, with the Arguments of each Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, which ſupply the place of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Paraphraſe upon the Books of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> and the <hi>Song of Solomon:</hi> With Arguments to each Chapter, and Annotations thereupon. In <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo.</hi> New.</item>
               <item>A Book for Beginners: Or, A Help to Young Communicants, that they may be ſitted for the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and receive it with profit.</item>
               <item>A Friendly Debate between a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt and a Non-Conformiſt. In Two Parts. The Sixth Edition Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and Englarged.</item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and
<hi>Frequency</hi> of rece ving the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: With a <hi>Reſolution of Doubts</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64584:103"/>about it. In three Diſcourſes, begun upon
<hi>Whitſunday,</hi> in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Peterburgh.</hi> New.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>Winter-Evening Conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Neighbours. In Two Parts. The Second Edition Corrected, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Old Religion demonſtrated in its Principles, and deſcribed in the Life and Practice thereof. In <hi>Twelves.</hi> New.</item>
               <item>22 Sermons preach'd partly before His Majeſty at
<hi>Whitehall,</hi> and partly before <hi>Anne</hi> Dutcheſs of
<hi>York,</hi> at the Chappel at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>James</hi>'s. By <hi>Henry Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligrew,</hi> D. D. Maſter of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and Almoner to his Royal Highneſs. New, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Animadverſions upon a Book, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Fanaticiſm Fanatically</hi> impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> by Dr.
<hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> and the Imputation Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed and Retorted by <hi>S. C.</hi> By a Perſon of Honour. The Third Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The End of the Catalogue.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
